<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jus regium coronæ, or, The King's supream power in dispensing with penal statutes more particularly as it relates to the the two test-acts of the twenty fifth, and thirtieth of His late Majesty, King Charles the Second, argu'd by reason, and confirm'd by the common, and statute laws of this kingdom : in two parts / auctore Jo. Wilsonio J.C.</title>
            <author>Wilson, John, 1626-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2921A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43961</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42476515</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42476515</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151466</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96658)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151466)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2260:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jus regium coronæ, or, The King's supream power in dispensing with penal statutes more particularly as it relates to the the two test-acts of the twenty fifth, and thirtieth of His late Majesty, King Charles the Second, argu'd by reason, and confirm'd by the common, and statute laws of this kingdom : in two parts / auctore Jo. Wilsonio J.C.</title>
                  <author>Wilson, John, 1626-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 79 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills ... and are sold at his printing-house ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First part only. No more published. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prerogative, Royal --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151466:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Jus Regium Coronae:</hi> OR, The KING's Supream Power in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing with Penal Statutes: More particularly as it relates to the two Teſt-Acts of the <hi>Twenty Fifth,</hi> and <hi>Thirtieth</hi> of His Late Majeſty, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, <hi>Argu'd by Reaſon,</hi> And Confirm'd by the Common, and Statute Laws of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Two Parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auctore</hi> Jo. Wilſonio. J.C.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Sir <hi>Edw. Coke, 1</hi> Inſt. <hi>64.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Imperij Majeſtas, Tutelae Salus.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty, for His Houſhold and Chappel; And are ſold at his Printing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe on the Ditch-ſide in <hi>Black-Fryers.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151466:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151466:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE SOCIETY OF Lincolns-Inn.</head>
            <p>IT is my Honour (Gentlemen) that I ſerv'd a double Apprentiſhip within your Walls; and however I have for many years diſcontinu'd, it is not poſſible, that any Man bred in a Society of ſo much Learning and Air, ſhould have alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether forgotten, what he once imbib'd.</p>
            <p>The Loyalty of your Houſe, (excepting ſome ſingle Perſon here and there) was in the worſt of times exemplary; Nor were Ye laſt, in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King back again to His: And becauſe the Diſpenſing Power beſt ſecures Him in it, and the Kingdom under it, unto whom more juſtly could I make a Proof of it, than to that Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Body, from whom I receiv'd it?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151466:3"/>
            <p>Such (Gentlemen) is the Diſcourſe I herewith preſent Ye; and in that, being now, no longer mine, but Yours, as none are more able, be alſo as pleas'd to defend it: Or ſo kind (at leaſt) to ſay this of Your old Acquaintance: That he ſpoke his Thoughts; That he believ'd them true; And on that account, would not willingly quit them, till he be better inform'd.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Humble Servant, <hi>John Wilſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:151466:3"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE FIRST PART.</head>
            <list>
               <label>SECTION. I.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> THat the rigor of Penal Laws were inſupportable, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome Supream Power, above thoſe Laws, to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that rigor, and diſpenſe with them, as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come inconvenient.—Eſpecially, when all Human Actions are ſubject to Corruption, and what might fit one time, may be the bane of another. Examples of it, in the <hi>Lacedemonian Ephori.</hi>—The <hi>Roman Decemviri.—Dictator.—Triumvirat.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>SECT. II.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> THat this Power cannot lie in any Select part of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or in the whole: Therefore, it muſt be in the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Prince, or Abſolute Monarch: And ſuch, the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have ever been, and now, are.—Examples of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſince the Conqueſt.—Further prov'd from Common Law, and Statute Law.—The King is ſole Legiſlator; and Interpreter of thoſe Laws.—That it appears not to have been ever the intent of God, that the People ſhould have any ſhare in the Government, but rather the contrary. That the Supream Power was not deriv'd
<pb facs="tcp:151466:4"/>from the People; or given in Truſt, by them; but radically in the Prince, as reſerv'd to Him, from the firſt Origin of Power, and before any poſitive, or written Law; at what time, Men were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by a Natural Equity.</item>
               <label>SECT. III.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> THat without this Supream Power, the King were in a worſe condition than the Subject.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Any Reſtriction on the means of Livelyhood of a Subject is void. <hi>A Fortiore</hi> on any neceſſary part of the Government.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> A Subject, on ſome Accidents may break a Law, yet not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Law. <hi>A fortiore</hi> the King, when the Kingdom is in danger, of which Himſelf is the ſole Judge, whither actual, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectant.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> A Subject, ſhall juſtifie a particular wrong, for a public Good. <hi>A fortiore</hi> the King, for a common Benefit:</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Where the Subject is enabled to the greater, he is of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence enabled to the leſs. <hi>A fortiore</hi> the King—He may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the higheſt Offences; much more prevent any leſſer matter, from becoming an Offence.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>SECT. IV.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> THat no Government can be entire, that is defective, in any neceſſary part: And therefore all Governments, beſides the power of the Sword, have ever pretended to this Supream Power as a <hi>Sine quo non.</hi>—Both Powers diſcuſt.—That even our moſt prudently deſign'd Conſtitutions, have turn'd to hurt; prov'd, from a Series of our own Hiſtories.—That every of the late <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpt Powers (as we call'em) frequently made uſe of this Supream Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Diſpenſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—An Anſwer to that common Objection, That the King is ſworn.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:151466:4"/>
               <label>SECT. V.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> THe Caſe of the <hi>Teſt, 25 Car.</hi> 2d. ſtated, and that His Majeſties granting Commiſſions, to certain Perſons, not qualify'd according to the ſaid Act; and yet retaining them in His Service, is warrantable by the Law of Reaſon, and the Laws of the Land.—<hi>By the Law of Reaſon.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Whither we take the Argument, <hi>Ab Honeſto, Ab utili,</hi> or <hi>à Tuto.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> The King is bound to defend, according to the beſt of His skill: Who ſhall be Judge of that skill, Himſelf, or the People?</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> What damage to the whole, that the King makes uſe of ſome part, without excluding the reſt? Or if it were a damage, it is but <hi>Damnum ſine injuria.—By the Laws of the Land.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> As the King is bound to defend, the Subject is bound to obey: And this Service of the Subject, is due to the King by the Law of Nature, which cannot be taken away, no, not by Act of Parliament.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> A further proof, That the King is ſole Judge of the danger of the Kingdom, and how, and when it is to be prevented, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> The Law requires nothing to be done, but it permits the way, and means of doing it; elſe, it were Imperfect, Lame, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt. —The King is to defend, ſhall He not chuſe His Souldiers?</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> A mixt Argument of Law, and Reaſon, from the time when the King granted thoſe Commiſſions.—The <hi>Teſt</hi> examined: When made—By whom carry'd on—To what end.—There was <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum flagrans</hi> at the time when thoſe Commiſſions were given out.—And that His Majeſties yet retaining thoſe Officers, falls under the ſame Reaſon, and Law.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>SECT. VI.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> THat the Statute has created a diſability in the Perſon, and other Objections anſwered.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1. Object.</hi> Grounded on the Diſabilities created by the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Statutes of <hi>31 El. c. 6.</hi> againſt <hi>Simony.</hi>—The <hi>Vendee</hi> of an Office, contrary to the <hi>5 Ed. 6. c. 16.</hi>— And the not taking
<pb facs="tcp:151466:5"/>the Oath of Supremacy, according to the <hi>5 El. c. 1.</hi> ſeverally an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, and prov'd, not to be under the ſame Reaſon.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2. Object.</hi> That the King had other hands—A Loyal City.—A truſty <hi>Militia. Anſw.</hi> But is the King bound to make uſe of them in extraordinary Caſes?—The King is <hi>Solus Rex, &amp; ſemper Rex.</hi>—He may charge the Subject, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>— And Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, without Parliament, with Inſtances of both.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3. Object.</hi> Grounded on the vacating the Judgment for the King, in the Caſe of Ship-Mony, by the Houſe of Lords in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament <hi>1640.</hi> Anſwer'd, And the King vindicated; by truly ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Caſe, between His Majeſty and that Parliament.—Their evil treating Him, before the Commons Murder'd Him.—That He was Virtually, tho' not Formally, under a Force—And that, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority without Power, is meerly imaginary.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>SECT. VII.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> THe Sum of the whole further aſſerted, and confirm'd from ſeveral Statutes, and other Authorities of the Common Law.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> That there are ſeveral things ſo incident in Power, to the King, that it is not in the power of a Parliament to take them away.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> That both Kings, and Parliaments, have been ever tender, of having them encroacht on, as may appear by the Savings, in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Acts of Parliament.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3</hi> That the power of Diſpenſing, or granting <hi>Non Obſtantes,</hi> to Penal Statutes, is one of thoſe Incidents, and that, inſeparable.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> That Statutes derogatory to the Prerogative, have ſome of them, been held for void; others, revok'd by the King ſolely.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> Examples of Perſonal Diſabilities, ſome Created by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; others, by Eccleſiaſtical Canons, diſpenſt with by the King; others, void in themſelves.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> The King cannot deveſt Himſelf, or reſtrain His Succeſſor, of any regal Right, that is Eſſentially, in the Crown.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151466:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Jus Regium Coronae, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The Firſt Part.</head>
               <head type="sub">In which (among other things) the Statute <hi>25 Car. 2.</hi> is diſcuſs'd: and prov'd, that the King may diſpenſe with it.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have taken upon me an Argument, the King's Supreme Power in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing with Penal Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in nevertheleſs (If all Knowledge be but Remembrance, and the mind of Man knoweth all things, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demandeth to have her own Notions excited, and awaked) I hold my ſelf the more excuſable, in as much as I broach no new Opinion, but only call to remembrance what unbias'd Men know well enough, if they would but recollect; and therefore without further Apology, I ſhall keep my ſelf to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod I propos'd in the Contents, and begin with the firſt.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151466:6"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. I.</hi> That the rigor of Penal Laws were inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, without ſome Supreme Power above thoſe Laws, to temper that rigor, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſe with them, as they ſhall become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HAd the World continu'd, as when God ſaid of it, <hi>And behold all things were very good!</hi> Or at leaſt in the condition, of which the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>who having no Law, were a Law to themſelves,</hi> there had been no uſe of Laws; Mankind had followed the dictates of Nature, and done to every one as they would have been done to themſelves: But when that great Impreſs began to be obliterated, and Man took no other meaſures, than what his own Will, or private Intereſt (how repugnant ſoever to the well-fare of the whole) prompted, Princes (the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Fathers of their Countries) as well to obviate the Diſtemper, as to keep peace among their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, firſt bethought them of Laws, and gave them; That ſuch as would not do what they ought to do, for the love of Virtue, might yet be deterr'd from doing what they ought not to do, for fear of the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Laws therefore (like ancient Statues) were drawn bigger than the Life, that they might be ſeen
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151466:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>at diſtance, and perform the Office of a <hi>Pharos,</hi> in giving notice of a dangerous Shoar: <hi>Eſto,</hi> and <hi>Sunto,</hi> was their beſt Language, and that too under the greateſt ſeverity, and largeſt comprehenſion, that no one might preſume to think himſelf exempted. And now, ſince it is not in Man that he be impecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but that even the moſt cautious, ſome time or other fall foul of thoſe Laws, and much more they, that never heed their ſteps, What would become of every Man, if the rigor of Law ſhould be let looſe upon him? Whoſoever but ſtumbles on it, is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of bruſing, and on whom ſoever it falls, it cruſheth him to pieces: In ſhort, <hi>The wringing of the Noſe cauſeth Blood</hi> (ſaith <hi>Augur</hi>) and if every man's actions ſhall be ſtretch'd, as far as they may be ſtrein'd, who knows what bloody conſtruction may be made of them? To go no further than our own Penal Statutes, ſome obſolete, others by proceſs of time become apparently impoſſible, or inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to be perform'd; What work have they in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, made among the People? Have they not been ſuch Thorns in their ſides, or rather Snares, to vex and entangle them, that <hi>Pluet ſuper eos laque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os,</hi> might but too truly be ſaid of them? And is any man ſo ſecure at preſent, that he is ſure, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can reach him? Has he ſo waſh'd his Hands in Innocence, that he but thinks, he could ſay, <hi>In nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo erratum eſt?</hi> I am apt to believe all men have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended more or leſs, and conſequently, cannot be without ſome apprehenſions of danger: Even Oxen
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151466:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>boggle at a Slaughter-houſe; And Man, of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is moſt uneaſie with a Sword over his Head: How neceſſary then is it, that there be ſome Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power above thoſe Laws, to temper their Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, and diſpenſe with them, as they ſhall become inconvenient: where, by diſpenſing, I mean the Relaxation of a Law, whereby that is permitted to be done, which otherwiſe, the Law had prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited.</p>
                  <p>Nor would I be ſo taken, as if I carry'd the leaſt Eye, againſt any Law that concerns Property; No; I confine my ſelf to ſuch Laws as reſpect Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and which by reaſon of unforeſeen accidents that may happen, or the neceſſity of State that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it, are in their own nature diſpenſible, for as much as (Acts of Parliament being but <hi>Leges tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> and made for the preſent occaſion) it may ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that what was meant for the preſervation of the Government, may by a Viciſſitude of time turn to the deſtruction of it. The cleareſt Waters will gather a Sediment, and the freſheſt Streams run down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Salt Sea of corruption; And therefore if Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhall not by Induſtry and Policy, keep head againſt the inclination of Time, all Inſtitutions be they never ſo pure, will corrupt, and degenerate.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Lacedemonian Ephori,</hi> were at firſt, ſo many Aſſiſtants to their Kings, but what by the corruption of Time, and Manners, and the want of a Cheque on them, overtop'd the Monarchy.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151466:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>In like manner the <hi>Decemviri</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> primarily intended for the better adminiſtration of Juſtice, in making a ſupply, to ſuch Laws as they wanted, and rectifying, and amending ſuch as were faulty; prov'd a Remedy, worſe than the Diſeaſe, and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Tyranny.</p>
                  <p>Add to this, That their ſo often ſucceſsful Officer of <hi>Dictator,</hi> or <hi>Populi Magiſter,</hi> (for there lay no Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal from him to the People) was never choſen for above ſix Months at one time; nor then either, but upon ſome imminent danger, and to avoid the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of ſeveral Commands; Yet that ſo cautelouſly deſign'd preſervative of their Liberty, became at laſt, its deſtruction, in <hi>Julius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And laſtly, The <hi>Triumvirat</hi> of <hi>Auguſtus, Antonius,</hi> and <hi>Lepidus,</hi> promis'd fair, for ſetling the Common-Wealth, but proſcrib'd it into Confuſion. So Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally impoſſible it is, that any condition, or State of Men, or Conſtitutions of their making, be the ſame in all Times, or ſute with all occaſions; and therefore, Remedies ought to be provided, as faſt as Time breeds miſchief. The firſt Man being in Perfection, abided not; and what may be expected of his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, all Ages have found;
<q>
                        <l>Damnoſa quid non imminuit dies?</l>
                        <l>Aetas parentum pejor avis, tulit</l>
                        <l>Nos nequiores, mox daturos</l>
                        <l>Progeniem Vitioſiorem.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151466:8"/>
                  <p>Of abſolute neceſſity then it ſeems, That there be ſome Supreme Power to rectifie the miſchiefs of Time and Chance, and by rectifying the rigor of Temporary Laws, or diſpenſing with their incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, render them, and their burthen the eaſier; And where this Power lies, ſhall be the Subject of the next Section.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. II.</hi> That this Power cannot lie in any Select part of the People, or in the whole: Therefore, it muſt be in every Sovereign Prince, or Abſolute Monarch; And ſuch the Kings of <hi>England</hi> ever have been, and now are, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN any Select part of the People it cannot lie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no part can be greater, or have more Power than the whole; and in the whole, it cannot, for they are ſubject to the Law themſelves, as more particularly made, to curb their Exorbitancies, and keep that ſo much talk'd of Liberty, from running into Licentiouſneſs: It remains then, that it lie in the Prince, <hi>i.e.</hi> A Sovereign Prince, or Abſolute Monarch, who if he offend againſt thoſe Laws, is unaccountable to them,<note place="margin">Bract. l. 1. c. 8, 1. Inſt. 1. b.</note> as having no Superior in his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151466:8"/>Dominions but God: And if this yet requires a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Explanation, To have <hi>Merum Imperium,</hi> an entire Empire,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sir</hi> J. Davys. <hi>61.</hi>
                     </note> and all the Liberties of an Empire in His Kingdom, is to be an Abſolute Monarch: But ſuch the Kings of <hi>England</hi> ever had, and now have: Therefore the Kings of <hi>England</hi> are Abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs.</p>
                  <p>Such was <hi>Edgar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anno Dom. 964. 4 Inſt. 359.</note> who wrote himſelf <hi>Anglorum Imperator, &amp; Dominus;</hi> and call'd his Kingdom, an Empire. — In the Laws of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Leg. <hi>Ed.</hi> c 17.</note> the King is ſtiled, <hi>Vicarius Dei in regno ſuo.</hi> —The 16 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. declares, The Crown of <hi>England</hi> hath been free in all Times, and in no Earthly Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, but immediatly to God. — <hi>Edward</hi> IV. is called <hi>Supremus Dominus noſter Rex,</hi> &amp;c. Which excludes all co-ordinate Authority. —The 24 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. further declares, That by ſundry old Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Hiſtories, and Chronicles, it is declared, and expreſſed, <hi>That this Realm of</hi> England, <hi>is an Empire, and hath been ſo accepted in the World.</hi> —And the 28. of the ſame King, <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>That the Kings of</hi> England, <hi>are Lawful Kings, and Emperors of</hi> England, <hi>and</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: which are no introductive, but declaratory Statutes; For they ſay not, what the King, and his Kingdom ſhall be, but affirm, what they anciently have been, and now are. —Laſtly, The 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 21. —The 1 <hi>El. c.</hi> 1. —and 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. agree in the ſame, and <hi>That the Crown of this Kingdom is an Imperial Crown.</hi> — In ſhort, all Offences are ſaid to be againſt the Peace of our Sovereign Lord the King,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151466:9"/>His Crown, and Dignity: And High Treaſon, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Ligeanciae debitum.</hi> —The Laws of <hi>England</hi> are called the King's Laws. —The Parliament, His Parliament;<note place="margin">22 E. 3.3.</note> and therein alſo, the King is ſole Judge, the reſt but Adviſers. —The Power of Calling, Proroguing, and Diſſolving them, is the King's. —Their ancient way of Addreſs, was by Petition to Him. —And the later Oaths of Supremacy, and Allegiance, acknowledge the King, <hi>The Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the Kingdom;</hi> And if this be not to be an Abſolute Monarch, what is? It is enough to me, that I have ſhewn the <hi>Apex poteſtatis,</hi> and where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that lies, there lies the Government, and puts it out of queſtion, whether this Supreme Power lie in the King, or the People.</p>
                  <p>But to proceed; I ſaid before, it could not lie in the People, and (I conceive) made it out, that it muſt be in the King; however, to make it yet more clear, we'll put both on the Ballance, and let moſt weight carry it.</p>
                  <p>The People, take them in <hi>Senſu Compoſito,</hi> and what are they but an unwieldy Lump of every thing, and nothing? And in <hi>Senſu diviſo,</hi> a kind of Sheep without a Shepherd; Every one of them, has a frisk by himſelf: One is for this Law, another for that, a third againſt both, a fourth againſt all, and ſo to the laſt, as the Worm bites; <hi>Quot homines tot Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> ever was, and ever will be: whereas the King, beſides that he hath but one mind, and that, directed to the good of the Community, the Law preſumes, He
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151466:9"/>can do no wrong, as being beſt able to judge of thoſe Laws, of which Himſelf, is both Maker, and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter: Both Houſes may Vote, and Reſolve as they pleaſe; In the Royal Sanction only, lies the Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, and that <hi>Vis plaſtica,</hi> that gives the <hi>Embrion</hi> Life, and quickens it into Laws: The King makes Laws, with the Conſent of the Lords, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, not the Lords and Commons, with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the King; which ſhews, that the Legiſlative Power is ſolely in the King; For the Approbation, or Publiſhing of Laws in a Senate, proves not,<note place="margin">Bodin. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. Lib. 1. cap. 8.</note> the Majeſty of the State, to be in the Senate: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, it neceſſarily follows, that He be alſo the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter: And ſo <hi>Bracton, Ejus eſt Interpretari, cujus eſt condere:</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe <hi>Dyer: Where the words of the Law are ambiguous,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dyer. f. 37</note> 
                     <hi>We muſt ſubmit to the Declaration of the Law-giver The King, who by the Advice of His Learned Counſel, may (without calling a Parliament) expound the Law, where it is doubtful, as his Predeceſſors have done in like Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> —And Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> gives the Reaſon,<note place="margin">1 Inſt. f. 73 &amp; 99.</note> when he ſays, The King is, <hi>Caput Reipublicae &amp; Legis.</hi>—And in another place;<note place="margin">2 Inſt. f. 268</note> 
                     <hi>preſum'd to carry all the Laws</hi> (In ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio pectoris ſui) <hi>in his own Breaſt:</hi> And what he means by thoſe Expreſſions, unleſs it be, That as the Laws are the Kings Laws, His alſo is the Interpretation of them, and the Supreme Power of Diſpenſing with them, a wiſer Man than my ſelf may be to learn; which, from a Perſon (eſpecially in his later days) no Friend to Prerogative, I lay the more weight on, in as much
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151466:10"/>as one Affirmative of his, cannot but carry more force with every ſober Man, than all thoſe Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, he has ſo often jumbled againſt it.</p>
                  <p>Add to this, The People have nothing, but what they receved themſelves; Or if ever they had, they would do well to ſhew it (for Poſſeſſion, tho' by <hi>Diſſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin,</hi> is good againſt all men, but him that hath the Right) or otherwiſe, they cannot be ſaid to have given any Regality, which was never in them: For, as all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was Originally from God, it ſeems alſo, that it was never his intention that the People ſhould have any ſhare in it. When there were but two Perſons, as at firſt, God plac'd the Government in one, and ſaid to the Woman,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>en.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou ſhalt be under the power of the Man, and he ſhall rule over thee.</hi> —And to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Confuſion amongſt their Poſterity, eſtabliſh'd a Succeſſive Monarchy, in his Speech to <hi>Cain</hi> (tho' a Bad, and his Brother <hi>Abel</hi> a Righteous Perſon) and that only by the right of Primogeniture;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>d.</hi> 4.7.</note> 
                     <hi>His deſire ſhall be to thee, and thou ſhalt rule over him.</hi>—And from thence it Succeeded in <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Family, for almoſt 2000 years:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>d.</hi> 49.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Reuben, Thou art my Firſt-born, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence of Dignity and Power;</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) Honor and Authority, <hi>i.e.</hi> the Supremacy of both; Or as the Vulgar <hi>Latin, Prior in donis, Major in Imperio:</hi> And when he, with <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> were for ſeveral Crimes diſinherited by their Father, and the <hi>Primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniture</hi> fall'n to <hi>Judah,</hi> to him it is ſaid, <hi>Thy Brethren ſhall Honor thee, Thy Father's Children ſhall bow down to thee:</hi> And (<hi>ver.</hi> 10.) the Scepter entail'd to him.</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:151466:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Thus far in the World, and the People had no So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty in them, and if they cannot ſhew when or how they got it ſince, it remains, that it lie radically in the Prince, as innate, and inherent in his Perſon, and not deriv'd from the People, or given in Truſt by them, but reſerv'd, from the firſt Origin of Power.</p>
                  <p>Nor need I run from Home, to prove it ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves: For whence is it, that all Lands are mediately, or immediately held of the King,<note place="margin">1 Inſt. f. 1. f. 65. f. 85.</note> as Lord Paramount; but that they came firſt from the Crown?<note place="margin">12 H. 7.17.</note> Or that at the beginning all Adminiſtration of Juſtice was in one Hand, <hi>i.e.</hi> the Crown? But that it was innate in it:<note place="margin">7 Coke 13.</note> All Dominion was deriv'd from it, and what has not been granted from it, remains in it. There were Kings,<note place="margin">Ibid. 12 H. 7.</note> before any Poſitive or writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Laws, and Men were then Govern'd, by a Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Equity: And what more conſonant to it, than that a Sovereign Prince ſhould not be defective in any thing requiſite to the ſupport of that Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? When without it, He were but as a common Perſon: Nay, how truly might it be ſaid (in another ſenſe) <hi>Ecce homo factus eſt ſicut unus è nobis!</hi> Yet ſuch muſt the King be, if he cannot temper the rigor, or diſpenſe with the inconvenience of a Penal Statute: And there being a natural Equity alſo, that ſome ſuch Supreme Power be, for the common conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of all Men, which, for as much as it cannot lie in the People, it follows, that it be in the King, as innate in Him, and a Branch of His Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151466:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>which was, before Laws were, and is now become a part of the Law of the Realm:<note place="margin">2 Inſt. 496. Stan. pl. c. 162. <hi>Cow. Tit. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rog.</hi>
                     </note> And this, <hi>Cowel</hi> defines to be, <hi>That eſpecial Power, Preheminence, or Privelege, that the King hath in any kind, over and above other perſons, and above the Ordinary Courſe of the Common Law, in the Right of His Crown:</hi> Nor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Reaſon,<note place="margin">Lib. 2. f. 55.</note> for (as <hi>Bracton</hi>) <hi>Dominus Rex eſt ſupra om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes qui ad Coronam pertinent:</hi> And in another place, <hi>Rex non habet parem in regno:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lib. 4. S 1. bid. S. 5.</note> And again, <hi>Nec Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem niſi Deum: Our Lord the King</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is above all His Subjects:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">E. 3.19.</note> 
                     <hi>He has no Equal in his Realm; Nor Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior but God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if Acts of Mercy, and Goodneſs draw nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt God, how neceſſary is it that were they loſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where elſe, they ſhould be found in a King? <hi>A cheſcun Roy</hi> (ſaith the Book) <hi>apent per reaſon de ſon Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">E. 3. f. 2.9.</note> 
                     <hi>à faire Juſtice, &amp; Grace: It belongs to every King by reaſon of his Office, to do Juſtice, and ſhew Mercy.</hi> And what is Mercy, but a rebating the edge of the Law? —<hi>Quibus tamen &amp; qualiter miſerendum eſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ract. l. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>doceant eum merita, vel immerita perſonarum. But unto whom, and to what degree he ſhall be merciful, let the good or ill deſert of the Perſons direct him:</hi> Which fully proves, that the King is ſole Judge of this Mercy. When the King Pardons, He makes a total Remiſſion of the Offence, but when He Diſpenſes, He only prevents a matter (not otherwiſe evil, but as prohibited) from becoming an Offence. A Branch of an Act, 11 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>That no one againſt whom any Judgment,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Inſt. 42.</note> 
                     <hi>or Forfeiture was given, ſhould ſue for Pardon or Grace,</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:151466:11"/>was made void. —And it was an Article againſt Cardinal <hi>Woolſey,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. 93. Art. 37.</note> 
                     <hi>That he had forbidden to ſue for the Kings Favor, or Pardon:</hi> which (amongſt other things) is there ſaid, to be contrary to the King's High Honor, Prerogative, Crown, Eſtate, and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity Regal: Nor without Reaſon; for as a King's being tender of his People, is not the leaſt part of His Glory; ſo the intercepting thoſe Beams, gathers a Cloud between Him, and His People, and in a manner robs Him of the advantage of being kind to Himſelf.</p>
                  <p>To cloſe this; I have prov'd it of abſolute Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for the common convenience of all Men, that there be ſome Supreme Power, to temper the rigor of Temporary Laws, and diſpenſe with their inconvenience; And as fully prov'd, where this Power lies. —That the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have anciently been, and now are, Abſolute Monarchs: That the King's Prerogative is a part of the Law of the Land: —And that to Him only belongs Mercy, as well as Juſtice. In the next place we'll conſider it more particularly, as it relates to the King's Power of Diſpenſing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151466:12"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. III.</hi> That without this Supreme Power the King were in a worſe Condition than the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Word King,<note place="margin">4 Inſt. 352.</note> is <hi>Nomen Politicum,</hi> and imports that Politic Capacity, which never dies, but extends to all his Succeſſors, as well Kings, as Queens of <hi>England;</hi> Now if this Supreme Power (as before, and ſhall be further ſhewn in its proper place) be Innate, and Inherent in the Perſon of the King, and not deriv'd from the People, the ſame Reaſon that has in all times ſupported the Liberty of the Subject, makes ſtronger for this Power, without which, that Liberty had never been, at beſt, indeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: For neither can any Man grant, what he has not, nor defend, without the means of doing it: The Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject has receiv'd; But how? <hi>Ex Gratia:</hi> And can Favor be ſaid to deſtroy an ancient Right, which runs in Succeſſion? Trees, and Plants, give us Fruit, and Flowers, but the productive Virtue, ſtill remains in the Root: The Liberty of the Subject, is a precious thing; But to talk of Liberty, yet deny the Prae-exiſtence of a Prerogative, which firſt gave, and has ever ſince ſupported that Liberty, what were it but to reimagin, <hi>That Houſe on the Sand?</hi> The ſame Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, muſt, and will, have the ſame Effects.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151466:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Nor is this all; The King has common juſtice on his ſide:<note place="margin">Cap. 29.</note> No Free-man (ſaith <hi>Magna Charta</hi>) ſhall be Diſſeiſs'd of his Freehold, or Liberties; Which Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> thus gloſſes: <hi>Liberty</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is that Freedom which Subjects have: And if any Statute be made contrary to</hi> Magna Charta, <hi>it ſhall be holden for none.</hi> I leave this laſt, to the Learned; But if a Subject ſhall not be Diſſeiſs'd of his Liberties, and the King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, be reſtrain'd in His Prerogative, what alſo were it, but to put Him in a worſe Condition than the Subject? To examin this, but <hi>de ſimilibus, ad ſimilia,</hi> were Argument enough, but when the heavy Scale, turns all for the King, 't were the heighth of Injuſtice, to deny Him His Weight. For inſtance,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Any reſtriction upon a Subject,<note place="margin">2 H. 5.5.</note> from the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Exerciſe of his Trade, is void; though the Party himſelf, gave a Bond not to Exerciſe it.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Graveſend Barge</hi> Caſe. 10 <hi>Jac.</hi> C. Ban.</note> —Or that the Reſtriction, be but Temporary. —Or Exclude any one, and leave it not Free to all. —Nay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">21 E. 4.79. 11 Cok. 53. &amp; 85.</note> a Man ſhall not be Diſtrein'd (though for a juſt Duty) by any Inſtrument neceſſary to his Trade; As the <hi>Anvil,</hi> from a <hi>Smith.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">14 H. 8. 2 Inſt. 565. <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.6.</note> —<hi>Books</hi> from a <hi>Scholar.</hi> —The <hi>Mill-Stone</hi> from a <hi>Millar;</hi> as accordant to the Law of God; For it is a taking his Life to pledge, in taking away his Lawful means of liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: And this Mr. <hi>Latch</hi> calls <hi>A Fundamental Law,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Poſt-Office <hi>Caſe.</hi>
                     </note> and the contrary, <hi>A breach of the innate Liberty of a Free-born People.</hi> And ſhall a Subject claim an innate Liberty, and it be yet doubted of the Kings innate Prerogative, which the Law calls <hi>Libertas Regia:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bract. l. 1.</note>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:151466:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>—<hi>Privilegium Regis:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Britt. f. 27. Reg. f. 61.</note> —<hi>Droit le Roy: —Jus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium Coronae;</hi> And of which he is no more Depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, than of his Crown, or Life? Has God In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted the King with the Good of the Community, and ſhall he be retrench'd in the common Exerciſe of it? The Men of this Age might be too wiſe for Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes; a King without Power, is the ſame, as a King without Subjects.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A Subject may (upon ſome accidents) break a Law, yet not offend the Law; as in caſe of Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or for the avoiding a greater inconvenience,<note place="margin">Plowd. 18.19. 2 Inſt. 168.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such, and the like, being exempted by the Law of Reaſon, when the words of the Law, are expreſly againſt it: On which ground, tho' the killing a Man be Felony,<note place="margin">3 Inſt. 56.</note> yet for the inevitable neceſſity of ſaving his own life a man may kill another:<note place="margin">5 Coke 91.</note> —Or a Thief, attempting to Rob him on the Road: —Or in his Dwelling-Houſe: —Or breaking it by Night; and no Felony.<note place="margin">9 Coke 68.</note> —In like manner an Officer, if a Felon reſiſt, or fly from him, ſo that he cannot otherwiſe Arreſt him,<note place="margin">15 H. 7.2.</note> may kill him: —And the breaking of Priſon, is Felony; but not if the Priſon be on Fire. And now if Laws, may in caſe of a private Man, be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended by neceſſity, how much more, when the Kingdom is in danger, of which the Law, makes the King ſole Judge,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vid.</hi> Their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments by themſelves, <hi>in Quarto.</hi>
                     </note> whither actual, or expectant? As was reſolv'd by all the Judges (even <hi>Hutton</hi> and <hi>Crook</hi> concurring in that Point) in the Caſe of Ship-Mony.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151466:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p n="3">3. A Subject ſhall juſtifie a particular Wrong, for a Public Good: And rather than the Common-wealth ſhall ſuffer, the Law will turn ſome prejudice to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons. Every Man's Houſe is his Caſtle,<note place="margin">Dyer. 34.</note> yet a Sheriff (if refus'd entrance) may break it to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend a Felon: —Treſpaſs, is an offence againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of another, and always preſum'd, to be done <hi>Vi &amp; armis;</hi> yet juſtifiable for a common benefit; as to make Bulwarks in another mans Ground,<note place="margin">Dyer. 60. 3 Inſt. 84.</note> or dig <hi>Salt-Peter</hi> in his Out-houſes, for the defence of the Kingdom:<note place="margin">11 Coke 82. Dyer 36. 8 E. 4.18. 21 E. 4.28.</note> —To pull down Houſes in a public Fire: —To turn the Plow, on the Head-land of another, in favor of Husbandry: —And dry Nets on his Land, for the maintenance of Fiſhing; and all this, becauſe private prejudice, is repaird by public Utility. —Nay Mr. <hi>Prynn,</hi> juſtifies his Lords,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> Part. 4. p. 22.</note> and Commons, for laying Taxes on the People, for the public Good, tho' in truth, it was but to ſupport a Rebellion. And ſhall the King that hath the largeſt Stake in this public Good, want ſo neceſſary a part of the Government, as not to be able to diſpenſe with an inconvenient Statute, eſpecially, when the not doing it may endanger that Good, which is the end of all Laws? If a Subject may juſtifie (as before) <hi>à fortiore</hi> may the King, in the preſent Caſe: For, all poſitive Laws, being ſubordinate to the ſafety of the People, againſt which, even the Law of Property carries no force, it is but juſt, and reaſonable, that they give place to the Law of Nature, for common De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:151466:14"/>
                  <p n="4">4. Where the Subject is enabled to the Greater, he is of conſequence enabled to the Leſſer.<note place="margin">8 Coke 70.</note> A Man has power to make Leaſes, provided they exceed not three Lives, or twenty one years: he may Leaſe for Ninety nine years; if three Lives live ſo long; for 'tis a leſſer Eſtate: <hi>à fortiore,</hi> where the King is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to the Greater, ſhall He not alſo be enabled to the Leſſer? He can Pardon, what hinders but he may prevent? Witch-craft, and Hereſie, are Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt the firſt Table, yet the King may Pardon both: how much more then, Diſpenſe with any thing, no Offence againſt the ſecond Table? Nor ſhall I believe but the Commons of that Parliament that brought in this, and the later Teſt, were of Opinion, that His Majeſty might diſpenſe with them, till I am better enform'd, what was the meaning of that Addreſs of theirs to the King,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jan.</hi> 20. 1680.</note> wherein they ſay, It was their Opinion, <hi>That the Proſecuting</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Diſſenters, <hi>upon Penal Laws, is at this time, grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to the Subject, and dangerous to the Peace of the Kingdom:</hi> And what meant they be not Proſecuting, but that they might, nay ought, to be diſpens'd with? 'Twas their Opinion in one Caſe, 'tis the King's in another; <hi>And ſhall not the Lord be</hi> (at leaſt) <hi>as his Servant?</hi> But to go on with the Argument.</p>
                  <p>High Treaſon is the moſt heynous of all others <hi>(Crimen laeſae Majeſtatis)</hi> and yet the King may Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don it,<note place="margin">3 Inſt. 211.</note> or any part of the Execution; or all, ſaving part. —The Sentence for Felony is Hanging; yet the King may alter it to Beheading: As the Lord
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151466:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>H.</hi> 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8 —<hi>Edward</hi> Duke of <hi>S.</hi> 5 <hi>E.</hi> 6.—The Earl of <hi>C.</hi> 7 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. and others Attainted of Felony, yet Beheaded. —The Judgment againſt a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for Treaſon, is Burning; yet the Counteſs of <hi>S.—Anne</hi> of <hi>B.</hi> and others in <hi>H.</hi> VIII's time.— And the Lady <hi>J. G.</hi> 1 <hi>Mary,</hi> Attainted of High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, were Beheaded.</p>
                  <p>And is not the Body more than Raiment? Shall the King have the Power of Life and Death, and yet be reſtrain'd in a matter of indifferency? Shall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man be Lord and Judge in his own Family, and the King alone be curb'd in His, the Kingdom? Shall he always ſee with other mens Eyes, hear by other mens Ears, and He that is to ſet Copy's to others, have His hand held, for fear of blotting? Let them that are of that Opinion, make it their own Caſe: If preſervation is to be preferr'd before Benefit, it neceſſarily follows, That there be ſome Ultimate Judge of the Means.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:151466:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> That no Government can be entire, that is defective in any neceſſary part; and therefore all Governments, beſides the Power of the Sword, have ever preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to this Supreme Power, as a <hi>ſine qua non, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BY an entire Government, I intend ſuch a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as carries in its ſelf all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the Defence of its ſelf, and all its parts; without which, it were defective, and conſequently, as no Government, becauſe it could neither encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dangers from Abroad, nor obviate, unexpected Emergencies at Home: Now if the power of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the means of doing this, be of abſolute neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to all Governments, and that it will be hard to find any Age ſo innocent, wherein ſome Law or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, has not been brought in (not to ſay obtruded) by Intereſt, or Faction, it ſeems of as abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, that every Government carry alſo in its ſelf, The power of diſpenſing with Laws, which, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever at their firſt making, might be proper enough, yet upon other Reaſon of Affairs, may prove incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, or be thought, may become ſo, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fit to be diſpens'd with: For Prevention is as neceſſary as Defence, and wiſe Men meet Dangers
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151466:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>half way; and the not doing it (what <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> told his <hi>Athenians</hi>) like Country-Fellows at Cudgels, that never ward a Blow till ſtruck.</p>
                  <p>To examine it a little: That there can be no Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety without Government, needs no proof; and that there can be no Government that anſwers not the end of Government, which is Common Safety, needs as little; for without it, what were Peace, but a mere Notion? A kind of Truce, or Ceſſation, no laying down of Arms. To ſupport this therefore, all Governments have not only pretended to the Power of the Sword, but as a Conſequent of that, to this other of Diſpenſing. I ſhall but touch the former, becauſe I take it for granted, as an inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble incident to the Sovereign Power; for the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Sword, being for the Defence, and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the People, is ſubſervient to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and muſt needs belong to him, with whom God hath entruſted the Government, as a neceſſary requiſite, without which, He cannot perform that Truſt: For what were it but a thing in Name, if it had nothing to work on, or how could it ſubſiſt, without a Command over the People? Or be more called Government, than a Cripple, or a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique, an entire Man; inaſmuch as the one, wants his Limbs, the other, the uſe of them? And what ſhall we talk of a power of Commanding, without a power of exacting Obedience to thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands? All Government were precarious without it, and men would Obey, but as themſelves liſted.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151466:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>Nor is it more poſſible there could be Order without it; and where that's wanting, there muſt be Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: <hi>Una Euruſque Notuſque ruunt</hi>—And what was the Effect of it? — <hi>Ad litora fluctus.</hi> In a word, Brambles grow at both ends, but the croſs-encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Sap, withers the middle: How neceſſary then is it, that there be ſome Ultimate Judge, whoſe Dictates be Concluſive? for to admit them Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, were to ſuppoſe a poſſibility of Erring; the leaſt apprehenſion of which, begets Diſputing; that, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; thoſe Factions; and they, every thing: By theſe ſteps, crep up the Parliament of 1640. and therefore, made it one of their <hi>De quibus non diſſeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum:</hi> That Egg, not cruſh'd in the Shell, might have broken into a Serpent, and ſpoild all. —What ſhall I add? <hi>Moſes,</hi> no ſooner nam'd a God to his People, than he brings Him in ſpeaking, <hi>Let there be Light, and it was ſo:</hi> He gave them no time to think; as (perhaps) doubting, they might have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, if not the thing, His Power over them.</p>
                  <p>In like manner, for the Power of Diſpenſing with Penal Laws, which is but a Concomitant of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.—It is God alone that can comprehend all things at once; paſt, preſent, and to come, are the ſame with Him, and, <hi>I Am,</hi> bears no diſtinction of Tenſes: Whereas Man, concluding only from the more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable of the Premiſſes, how is it poſſible for him to foreſee all the intercurrencies, and perplexities of Time, and Chance; at beſt, ſo ſufficiently, as to be ſecure againſt them? The beſt Gameſter
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151466:16"/>cannot prevent all Blots, and the moſt expert Marks-man may ſometimes carry over, as well as not reach home: And therefore, becauſe in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Laws, it is as impoſſible, as in Philoſophy, to find (the <hi>Maximum quod ſit,</hi> or <hi>Minimum quod non</hi>) That indiviſible Point of Proportion, or ſufficiency, juſt ſo much as will do, and no more; as impoſſible (I ſay) as to make a Shoe ſhall fit every Foot, any Rule ſo general, as ſhall admit no exception, or Law ſo abſolute, but that in ſome Caſe or other, there is no Proviſion made; or ſhall not fail in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; or by Corruption of Time, not corrupt with it; It is of abſolute neceſſity, that the Government, whatever it be, have the Supreme Power, of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Temporary Laws, and proviſional Remedies, to their firſt intention, or diſpenſe with them, as they prove inconvenient, and therefore fit to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpens'd with, till they ſhall be better Abrogated. I inſtanc'd erewhile, in the days of Old; but as I come nearer to my Matter, I'll come nearer Home; And let him that Reads me without prejudice, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult our own Hiſtories, and he'll find, that even our beſt Conſtitutions, how prudently ſoever at firſt intended, have by the ſame Corruption of Time, and Manners, not only fail'd in their end, but on the contrary, turn'd to hurt.</p>
                  <p>I ſaid before, That at the begining, all Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Juſtice was in one Hand, <hi>i.e.</hi> The Crown, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But as People encreas'd, this Adminiſtration, was divided into Counties, and the King appointed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151466:17"/>His Deputy, in every County to be Conſervator of the Peace at Home, and defend it from Enemies from abroad; who was called, The <hi>Ealderman,</hi> Earl, or Shyreeve, <hi>i. e. Praepoſitus Comitatus</hi> (for ſo the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) and is our now Sheriff; But this anſwer'd not the intention: For the Office being at that time granted in Fee, with a <hi>Tourne,</hi> County-Court, and a third penny of the County, to ſupport the Dignity, they became ſo obnoxious to the Crown, that they led their Counties as they pleas'd themſelves, and not often, againſt it: to leſſen this growing Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as our Kings afterwards granted Lands, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo granted <hi>Court-Leets,</hi> and <hi>Court-Barons,</hi> to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Lords of thoſe Seigniories, or Mannors; And what effect had that Royal Munificence? But that it ſo put them in the Head, of how much more Power was wanting, that in the <hi>17th.</hi> of King <hi>John</hi> (with Swords in their hands) they complain to Him, of an infringment of their Liberties (the firſt time, if I take it right, that any ſuch Liberty was ever talk'd of; For that of the Men of <hi>Kent,</hi> to <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> the Conqueror, was a formal Stipulation with a Conqueror, to whom as yet, they ow'd no Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Ligeance) and extort a Charter from Him, at <hi>Running-Mead,</hi> which laid the Foundation of the Barons Wars.</p>
                  <p>However, this was expediated for the preſent; and now the erecting of Borroughs, and Corporations (ſo many diſtinct Liberties in a County, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from either of them) might, one would have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151466:17"/>thought, been a prudent Expedient of leſſening both, and at firſt, it ſtruck well towards it; for as the one got ground, the other loſt it, but it laſted not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, without running into worſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> III. and his Father before Him, had been long turmoil'd with thoſe Barons Wars, and having at laſt, after a threeſcore years Rebellion (more by Factions amongſt themſelves, than any ſtrength of his own) got the better of them, began to conſider that thoſe Seditious Barons (for as yet the Commons were not any Conſtituent part of a Parliament) had brought Subjects to be more than they ſhould be, and Kings leſs than they were, and therefore (in the 52. of his Reign) calls a Parliament, and brought in the Commons, to counter-ballance them: And <hi>Edward</hi> l. (his Son) by calling ſome few of His Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons to Parliament by Writ (and that, <hi>pro hac vice tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi>) inſenſibly leſſened their number, and freed the Crown from the Wardſhip of His Barons.</p>
                  <p>And yet even this, anſwer'd not the Expectation; for as thoſe few that remain'd became the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, ſo the Staddles being not left too thick, the Underwoods, got up the eaſier: The Commons fell into a Foreign Trade, that Trade brought home Moneys; thoſe Moneys gave them footing in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of the Nobility, The device of common Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries (in <hi>Edward</hi> III's time) ſecur'd thoſe Eſtates, All together, gave them Reputation, and now who knew, but another Rebellion, might make them, Lords alſo?</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:151466:18"/>
                  <p>And now, Privilege, is ſet up againſt Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, nor could they long want ſome Diſcontent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Lords, to give it Countenance: The Crown was become neceſſitous, and indulg'd their Demands; and what was the effect of it? They take upon them to be Judges of the Right to the Crown, and accordingly, give up <hi>Richard</hi> II. to the undue pretences of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. and though they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and his Son, afterwards King <hi>Edward</hi> IV. to the recovery of their Right, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Henry</hi> VI. yet they ſet up <hi>Richard</hi> III. againſt their lawful King, <hi>Edward</hi> V. However <hi>Henry</hi> VII. deeming them of more uſe to Him than a topping Nobility, firſt clip'd the later's Wings, by the Statute againſt Retainers, and then, leſſened their Grandeur, by encreaſing their number: Since which, the Kings his Succeſſors, having added more, and not the leaſt ſhare of Abbey-Lands, fal'n to the Commons, what have all theſe prudent intentions prov'd, but a run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from one extream to another? And of what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage this laſt has been, let the Rebellion 1640. Witneſs.</p>
                  <p>There is one thing more, which I had almoſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: Gylds, Fraternities, and Corporations, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently (without queſtion) deſign'd at firſt, for the Advancement of Trade, by carrying it on with a common Stock; Regulating the Abuſe of Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures; keeping their Members in Obedience to the King, and the like: But have not they alſo, fall'n from the firſt intention? Is Trade in general, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151466:18"/>by it; Or has it not been made uſe of as a double Key, to Let-in ſome few, and Lock-out the greater number? Are Manufactures either improv'd, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifi'd; Or has not the knack of making them ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, crept in its room? And inſtead of Obedience to the King, have they not been the common Sourſe, and Fomenters of Sedition? If this (and what I have offered before) be true, it proves my Aſſertion; and if it be not, what means all this Lowing, and Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of the Herd? The firſt intention of Phyſick, was for Prevention, and Remedy, yet it often ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, that it joins with the Diſeaſe, and both work together, to the deſtruction of the Body. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon this matter, it ſeems to be of abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, that there be this Supreme Power; and that it be exerted in counter-working the injuries of Time, and Chance, by making proviſion for Contingencies, in the due application of occaſional Remedies, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, there would be a failer in Government. Now if this Power were ty'd up to ſuch <hi>(Dogmata adamantina)</hi> unalterable Decrees, that in no caſe whatever they were to be vary'd from, where were the uſe of it? The contrary has been the practice of all Ages, and therefore I ſhall not labor the Point at preſent, till I come to ſhew what the Kings of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> (and that <hi>de jure</hi>) have done in like caſes; of which, in its proper place.</p>
                  <p>However yet, before I leave it here, and becauſe alſo, I am wholly at home, it may not be amiſs to examin whether the late Uſurp'd Powers, did not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151466:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>look upon this Power of Diſpenſing, ſo abſolutely neceſſary to the carrying on their Arms againſt their Leige-Lord and Sovereign The King, that (to ſay nothing of the Divine Law) they not only diſpens'd with Statue-Law, but even the Common-Law too, which, where it made not againſt themſelves, they held indiſpenſible?</p>
                  <p>I ſhall begin with the Parliament I ſo lately men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, where Collonel <hi>Nath. Fienns</hi> (afterwards, one of their Commiſſioners for the Seal) tells them, <hi>That it is againſt the Law, and Light of Nature, for a Man to Swear never to conſent to alter a thing,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">His 2d. Speech to the Houſe. <hi>p. 13.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>which in its own Nature alterable, and may prove inconvenient, and fit to be altered:</hi> And that both Houſes were of the ſame Opinion, may be ſeen in this, that they acted accordingly: For by the Name, of the Lords and Commons in Parliament, they Ordain'd, and again made <hi>non Obſtantes</hi> to thoſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances. As <hi>9th. October</hi> 1643. — <hi>23th. May</hi> 47. —<hi>22th.</hi> and <hi>24th. April</hi> '48. —<hi>24th. July</hi> '48. —and <hi>16th. December</hi> '48. Repeal'd their own Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of <hi>29th. Auguſt</hi> '45. which is <hi>contra Conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem Parliamenti.</hi> Then again, as they grew higher, They Aboliſh'd Epiſcopacy, Any Letters Patents from the Crown, made, or to be made, or any other Authority whatſoever, any Law, Statute, Uſage, or Cuſtom to the contrary notwithſtanding. <hi>9th. October</hi> '46. —Sold Biſhops Lands with a like Clauſe <hi>23th. September</hi> '47. —And Abrogated the Feaſt of the <hi>Nativity,</hi> and all other Feſtivals call'd
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151466:19"/>
                     <hi>Holy-days,</hi> any Law, Statute, Conſtitution, or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, to the contrary notwithſtanding, <hi>3d. June</hi> '47.</p>
                  <p>Then, when they had killed, and taken Poſſeſſion, and Enacted themſelves, the Supreme Authority of the Nation (I ſpeak now, of the Commons, for I find no concurrence of the Lords, after the <hi>9th. Jan.</hi> '48.) they made <hi>non Obſtantes</hi> to their own Acts: As the <hi>8th.</hi> and <hi>19th. June</hi> '49. —Took away Tithes appropriate. <hi>8th. June,</hi> '49. —Recontinu'd Pleas in <hi>Durham. 19th. June,</hi> '49. —Sold Fee-farm Rents. <hi>27th. July,</hi> '50. —Set up Marrying by Juſtices. <hi>20th. Aug.</hi> '53. and ſeveral the like, and every of them, with this or the like clauſe; Any Law, Statute, Cuſtom, Uſage, Act, Ordinance, (and in the matter of the Purchaſers of Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi>'s E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate) or Judgment, to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
                  <p>And Laſtly, When they had play'd the Game into <hi>Oliver</hi>'s hand, was his Inſtrument of Government ſet to any other Meaſures? His Ordinances of the <hi>26th. Decemb.</hi> '53.—<hi>20th. March</hi> 53.—<hi>16th. May,</hi> '54.—<hi>2d.</hi> and <hi>9th. June,</hi> '54. and ſeveral others, carry the ſame, or like Clauſes: In all which, did they not more than im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, That the Power of Diſpenſing, was inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly incident to the Supream Authority, in whoſe hand ſoever it were?</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>But may ſome ſay, we know what they were; they had no Right; nor could better be expected from them: But now we have a Gracious King, Sworn to defend the Laws,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Very well. But then why do we doubt him in that defence? The Law ſays, He can do no
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151466:20"/>wrong; and ſhall we preſume he will do it? But does there nothing more lie under the Word <hi>Sworn?</hi> For fear there ſhould, I give it this further Anſwer: That when the Promiſe is not annext to the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (as in the caſe of a Soveraign Prince) but a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary condeſcention, that he will ordinarily govern by ſuch a Rule, his Eſtate is not thereby made conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; and tho' he be oblig'd in Honour to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, yet the Authority ceaſes not, if he fail in it; for the People ſtill owing him an abſolute Subjection, that Prior Subjection cannot be diſſolv'd, or leſſen'd, by any Subſequent Act of Grace. The King is to all Intents and Purpoſes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>7</hi> co. <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Caſe.</note> King, before Coronation; and conſequently, without that Oath which he makes at his Coronation. Nor does he promiſe more at that time, than he was Morally pre-oblig'd to do; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other, than a Free, Royal Promiſe, to diſcharge that Duty honourably, which the Laws of God, and Nature had requir'd of him without that Promiſe.</p>
                  <p>To bring the caſe home: Did thoſe Lords and Commons make, and vary Laws, according to the preſent condition of their Affairs? Had they the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of untying any Knot, their Sword was capable of cutting? Shall Men that had not the leaſt face of Right, make, and unmake, break, and diſpenſe with ſo many known Laws, to ſupport a Rebellion? And ſhall it be doubted, whither a rightful King may paſs by one ſingle Law, for the preventing, or ſuppreſſing another? Shall it be confeſt, Their Nobles broke the Band of Government; their Prophets, Propheſy'd
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151466:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>falſly; their Prieſtlings, Sanctify'd thoſe Ordinances; and a fooliſh People, lov'd to have it ſo? And yet be ſaid, The King is out of his way, when yet he keeps within his own Circle, and does no more than what the Law of Reaſon, the Law of the Land, as well as his Prerogative, warrant him the doing? The Matter of this firſt Teſt falls properly in: I'll ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine it a little, and leave every unbia'ſt Man to his own Judgment; wherein nevertheleſs, tho' it may be beyond my skill to make the deaf Adder hear, I hope I ſhall offer ſome reaſon yet, why he ſhould not hiſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. V.</hi> The Caſe of the Teſt (<hi>25 Car.</hi> 2d.) ſtated: And that his Majeſties granting Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to certain Perſons, not qualify'd ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Act; and retaining them in his Service, is warrantable by the Law of Reaſon, and the Laws of this Land, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Caſe upon this Matter will fall to be thus. His late Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d,</hi> in the <hi>25th.</hi> of his Reign, paſſes an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereby all Perſons, not taking the Oaths of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151466:21"/>Supremacy, and Allegiance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Subſcribing the Declaration, therein ſpecify'd, after the manner, and according to the time, by the ſaid Act limited (which for brevity, Men call the Teſt) ſhall be <hi>ipſo facto</hi> diſabled, to hold any Office, Civil, or Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. and the ſaid Office void, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Notwithſtanding which, I conceive, and doubt not but to prove, That his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties granting Commiſſions to ſuch, or ſuch Perſons, not qualify'd according to the ſaid Act, is no more than what is warrantable, by the Law of Reaſon, and the Laws of this Land.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall begin with the Law of Reaſon; and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we take the Argument, <hi>Ab Honeſto, ab utili,</hi> Or, <hi>à tuto:</hi> I conceive, every one of them makes for me. For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What Honour is it to be King of a People that He cannot command? What Profit, to have uſeleſs Perſons, that take up room, but bring no Honey to the Hive? Or what ſafety, when inſtead of an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my from abroad, He cannot ſay, He is ſecure at home? How muſt that Prince have behav'd himſelf, where His People fear him, not for him? What aſſiſtance can He expect from them, and have no reputation with them? Or what common ſafety to the whole, when neither dare truſt one another? And what muſt the conſequence of this be with the people? The People, who take nothing by a true Light, but as it is foiſted on them, through falſe Opticks: <hi>Vereſimile,</hi> is the ſame with them, as <hi>Verum,</hi> and if it but look
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151466:21"/>like it, 'tis the ſame, as if it were ſo: It naturally fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, That <hi>(Conflatâ magnâ Invidiâ, ſeu bene,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tacitus.</note> 
                     <hi>ſeu malè geſta premunt</hi>) having gotten a malicious Opinion by the end, let the Prince do well or ill, they'll be ſure to traduce him: Whereas the Staves of Beauty, and Bands, go together, but where there are Jealouſies, and Diviſions, there can be no Honour, Profit, or Safety to Prince, or People.</p>
                  <p>The Form of Government is that, which actuates, and diſpoſes every part, and Member, to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good of the whole; and as thoſe Parts, give Strength and Ornament to that whole, ſo they receive from it again, Strength and Protection in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Stations: Whereas, if this mutual Interchange of Concord, and ſupport be broken, it cannot be, but the whole muſt fall in pieces, for want of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Ligament, that kept it together: From whence I infer, That as to reſtrain his Majeſty from making uſe of any part of his Subjects, for the common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the whole, is a breach of that mutual Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change; ſo the granting thoſe Commiſſions, being a ſupport of it, were for the Honour, Profit, and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the King and Kingdom, and conſequently (as far as they have any force) warrantable.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The King is bound to defend his Subjects, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the beſt of his skill; and that, becauſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and Protection, are Relatives: And who now, ſhall be Judge of that skill, Himſelf, or the People? Who ſhall order a Battel, the General, or the Army? Who Preſcribe, the Phyſician, or the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient?
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151466:22"/>Or judge of the Helm, the Pilot, or the Ships-Crew? And is it not ſtronger on the King's ſide? Soveraignty is a Commiſſion granted by God to the Prince, who is the Soul that informs, and actuates, that incompacted Body, the People; and whoſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice it is to command: It is by the ſame Authority in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted to him, for the good of the Community; and ſhall he ſtand accountable to God, for the diſcharge of that Truſt, and yet be reſtrain'd by them, in the common exerciſe of it? Nay, is it not a diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Truſt, by diſabling the performance of it, in the Interdiction of the means? Or ſuppoſe he could transfer that Truſt, were it not a diſcharge of the power of executing it? And then, where lay the neceſſity of Obeying? For, Empire, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, being Correlatives, where the Right of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding ceaſes, the Duty of Obeying, ceaſes with it, and the Government is no longer from God, but the People. And here alſo, the granting thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, being but a juſt Aſſertion of that power, entruſted as aforeſaid, are alſo warrantable by the Law of Reaſon, and conſequently, well granted.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What damage is it to the whole, that the King makes uſe of any part, without excluding the reſt, who are equally oblig'd, to ſerve him with the reſt; in as much, as what concerns the whole, ought to be defended by the whole; and where the danger is general, the defence ought to be as general? Or if it were a damage, it were but <hi>Damnum ſine injuria,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Law of Nature (as I ſhall come to ſhew
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151466:22"/>preſently) wills it. Of what uſe is a Diamond in the Rock? Arms in an Arcenal, without Hands to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage them? Or Books in his Study, that dares not take them down, for fear of miſplacing? One half of the World lives by credit with the other half: No Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce or Traffick could be kept up without it; And even Princes themſelves, are ſecur'd at home, by their Reputation abroad. And does not this Reputation lie in Strength, <hi>i.e.</hi> the power of commanding their Subjects? And if any part of that ſtrength be taken off, is it not a leſſening the ſtrength of the whole? Or can that whole be ſaid to be ſafe, when any part lies unguarded? I cannot tell what the Men of the next Age may be, but experience has taught thoſe paſt, That the Tortoiſe, is ſecure within its Shell, but if any part lies out, all the reſt are in danger. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitably the ſame, muſt the Condition of that Prince be, who ſhall be thus wanting.</p>
                  <p>Whereas on the contrary, that of <hi>Dido</hi> to <hi>Aeneas,</hi>
                     <q>Tros, Tyrjuſque mihi nullo diſcrimine—</q> brings all to rights again: For the King is abridg'd in none of his Subjects: The Kingdom has its whole ſtrength: And every Man, becomes another Arrow to the Bundle. Here is no danger of Obſtructions, for the Circulation is clear: No Quarrel among the Children, for they are all alike to the Father: And no fear of a Diſcontented Party, when every one falls in to the ſupport of that whole, whereof he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151466:23"/>reckons himſelf a part. In a Word, tho' the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be of divers Colours, there's no Rent, or Seam in it: No Wound to feſter, or bleed inwards: No jarring ſtring to break the Harmony, or excuſe for ſtanding idle in the Market-place, when they may come in if they pleaſe. And therefore, theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions being of no damage, but on the contrary, a further Security to the Kingdom, I conceive them fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo warrantable by the Law of Reaſon, and conſequently (as far as that goes) well granted.</p>
                  <p>Nor are they leſs warrantable by the Laws of this Kingdom. For if the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> by common uſage, which is common Law, have without Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (nay during the time of their Sitting, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking the leaſt notice of them) by their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent power, grounded on the neceſſary reaſon of defence, commanded their Subjects to their aid; and if ſeveral Acts of Parliament, have declar'd, That the Subject owes the King a natural Obedience, and Alligeance, and are thereby bound to ſerve Him; then His Majeſty's now granting theſe Commiſſions, is alſo warranted by the Laws of the Land. And that it has been ſo done, and declared, I am coming to ſhew.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the King is to defend, and the Subject to obey,<note place="margin">Judge <hi>Hut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the King, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aſe of Ship-Mony.</note> needs no proof: An Act of Parliament, that he ſhould not do it, or have no aid from them, were void in its ſelf, becauſe it would be againſt natural Reaſon, ſaith Judge <hi>Hutton.</hi> And Judge <hi>Crooke,</hi> who alſo gave his Judgment againſt the King, in the ſame
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151466:23"/>Caſe, confeſſes, That when the good and ſafety of the Kingdom is in danger,<note place="margin">Judge <hi>Crcok</hi>'s Argument in the ſame Caſe.</note> the King may command all his Subjects to provide and furniſh Ships at Sea, with Men, Munition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at their own Charges: And this (ſaith he) I hold to be agreeable to Law and Reaſon. —<hi>Edw.</hi> the <hi>3d,</hi> in the <hi>10th, 11th,</hi> and <hi>12th.</hi> of his Reign (a Parliament then ſitting) ſent out his Writs for Aids, without taking any notice of them, or the leaſt complaint on their ſide, that the King had ſtretcht his Authority. — The two Chief Juſtices, and Lord Chief Baron (in the ſame caſe) ſaid, It was the conſtant practiſe in the Reigns of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. —<hi>Edw. 2d.—Edw. 3d.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Annals of <hi>Ch. I.</hi> Fol. <hi>599.</hi>
                     </note> And ſo agreeable to the Common Law of Kingdoms, That the King might compel the doing it, in caſe of refuſal. —No Age, Order, or Perſon exempted:<note place="margin">Ibid. An. f. <hi>517.</hi>
                     </note> So <hi>Rich. 2d.</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all Men between 16. and 60. to be in readineſs. —Writs to Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury—York.</hi> —Abbots, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That they, and all their Clergy,<note place="margin">1 <hi>H.</hi> 4.</note> ſhould <hi>Manus adjutrices apponere.</hi>—The like (of the ſame King) to ſeveral Counties of <hi>England,</hi> to array all the Lords <hi>(&amp; omnes homines defenſibiles)</hi> and all ſuch as were able to bear Arms; and thoſe that were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent, and could not go, to contribute.—The like in <hi>Hen 6th.—Hen. 7th.</hi>— and <hi>Hen.</hi> 8<hi>'s</hi> time.— And to the Cinque Ports,<note place="margin">48 <hi>H.</hi> 3.</note> That they come Day and Night to the King, when any danger is.—For (as Judge <hi>Jones,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. An f.</hi> 591. <hi>Br. Ten.</hi> 44.73. <hi>Fitz.</hi> N. B. 28. 7 Cok <hi>in</hi> Calv.</note> with whom alſo agrees our Statute Law) The King hath an intereſt in the Perſon of His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects <hi>pro bono publico</hi>—Or as need requires.—And may
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151466:24"/>diſpoſe of their Bodies for the defence of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Stat.</hi> 2 <hi>H.</hi> 4. c. 24. 9 <hi>H.</hi> 3. c 20. 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. c. 1. &amp; 18. 24 <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 12. 3 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. c. 2.</note> —Command them to go with Him (or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Him in His Service) as well without, as within the Realm. And the reaſon of all this is, becauſe they are bound by their Alligeance to ſerve Him, and this Alligeance due, by the Law of Nature. In ſhort, every Subject, is by reaſon of his Natural Alligeance bound to ſerve the King, when required by the King: But no Act of Parliament can diſcharge the Subject from this Natural Alligeance: Therefore every Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is bound to ſerve the King, when ſo required. To which if it be ſaid, a diſability, is no abſolute diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge. I anſwer, where lies the difference, as to the main, whither a parcel of Thieves kill a Man's Servants, or bind them ſo, that they cannot defend their Maſter?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The King is ſole Judge of the danger of the Kingdom, and how, and when, it is to be prevented, or avoided: Which alſo was acknowledg'd by <hi>Hut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and <hi>Crooke,</hi> in the Caſe before; and Mr. <hi>St. Johns</hi> in his Argument againſt the King,<note place="margin">Ibid. An. <hi>f. 483.</hi>
                     </note> ſays thus, <hi>The Sheriff has the</hi> Poſſe Comitatus, <hi>and therefore it follows, that the</hi> Poſſe Regni <hi>is in Himſelf.</hi> And ſhall the King have the Power of the Kingdom, and be thought not to know how to uſe it? Or if He does, where lies the Quarrel? Ought not the Judge of the danger to direct the means for avoiding it? Surely yes: It is not the Tenant by Caſtle-guard, but the Lord, that gives warning, of the Enemy; and the Reaſon is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> leſt the defence come too late.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:151466:24"/>
                  <p>The King by His Commiſſion, ſays, Such or ſuch a Perſon is fit for His Service; no averment lies againſt it: The King in a <hi>Ne exeat Regno,</hi> affirms,<note place="margin">1 Eliz. <hi>f.</hi> 105.</note> That <hi>I. S.</hi> will go beyond Sea: It is not traverſable.—What a Judge doth as in his Office,<note place="margin">Dyer. 163. 7 <hi>H.</hi> 7.40.</note> ſhall not be aſſign'd for Error. And ſhall any thing be wanting in the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that iſſues in the Stream? Shall the Delegate have more power than him that Delegates him? If no averment, or traverſe, ſhall be againſt the Act of a Judge, how much leſs then, where the King is abſolute Judge? Suppoſe there were but <hi>Vulgaris Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio</hi> in the caſe: Even common Fame is a ſufficient ground for prevention; for,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lord</hi> Bacon.</note> Fames are no leſs the preludes of Seditions to come, than the Relicks of Seditions paſt; and will the People never believe a Treaſon, unleſs the Prince be kill'd? The King has ſecret Intelligence, we know not, and muſt He make no preparation, without He reveal it? And if He ſhould, how long would it be a Secret?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Law requires nothing to be done, but it permits the way, and means, how it may be done; elſe the Law were Imperfect, Lame, and Unjuſt: Imperfect, for want of Proviſion; Lame, for want of Power; and Unjuſt, in requiring an Impoſſibility: A kind of ſending forth a Meſſenger, (as <hi>Solomon</hi>) and cutting off the Feet; whereupon it is a Maxim in our Law, <hi>That when the Law gives a Man any thing,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Inſt. 153. 11 Coke 52.</note> 
                     <hi>it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies alſo of that, without which the thing it ſelf could not be.</hi> As, a Man takes Ground of another, the Law implies, he ſhall have a way to it.<note place="margin">9 <hi>E.</hi> 4.35.</note> —Or has a Pipe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151466:25"/>running through another Man's Ground, he may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to mend it,<note place="margin">8 Coke 146. 9 Coke 11. 1 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 161.</note> as cauſe requires.—So, may the Lord, to diſtrein.—He in Reverſion, to view what waſte; and the like; for to take away the means, were to deſtroy the end. In like manner here: The Law ſays, The Intereſt, and Soveraignty of defending, is the King's; and ſhall it not alſo allow Him the means of doing it?—The King has the abſolute Power of Peace,<note place="margin">19 E. 4.6. 13 Car. 2. c. 6.</note> and War.—The Supream Government of all Forces by Sea and Land: And ſhall He be fore-judg'd the chooſing His Souldiers? 'Twas the ſhort <hi>(pro Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. honeſta)</hi> Saying of <hi>Galba,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tacitus.</note> when He refus'd a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native to ſome Mutinous Legions <hi>(Legi à ſe Militem, non emi)</hi> That he us'd to chooſe his Souldiers, not to give Mony for 'em: As well knowing, that the next demand had been the Empire; as indeed, it fell true in him; for what was that Power of the Sword, when he was not ſecure, of not having it turn'd upon himſelf? Or of what better uſe to any Prince, with a Pad-lock on the Scabbard? The <hi>Scots</hi> have a pat Word for it; <hi>A Feckleſs Tree-Sword.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Laſtly, there remains yet another Argument, that carrys in it, both Law, and Reaſon; there was a neceſſity upon His Majeſty at the time when he grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe Commiſſions: A Neceſſity, of preventing a Neceſſity: And who knows not, but Neceſſity is the Law of time, and action, and regulates the Law of the place? As that of <hi>David</hi>'s eating the Shew-Bread; and our caſting over Goods in a Storm. And who alſo is ſo great a ſtranger at home, that has not (at
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151466:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>leaſt) heard of thoſe preparatory Libels, and Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous <hi>Declarations</hi> (for ſome time before) nightly ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and daily communicated to Friends? What was the meaning of thoſe hollow Blaſts? Were they ever the Forerunners of Fair Weather? Or not of the contrary? 'Twas a ſhrewd Argument all was not well, or not like to continue well.</p>
                  <p>But before I go further, I muſt be forc't to look back, the way (in this caſe) to make haſte, being to ſtand a while and conſider.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The time when this firſt Teſt (for I ſhall not ſpeak to the other, till my ſecond part) was made.</item>
                     <item>2. By whom carry'd on.</item>
                     <item>3. To what end.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>As to the Firſt: It was in the Year 1673, at what time the Fears and Jealouſies of 1640 (like <hi>China</hi>-Earth laid in by the Grandfather) had fermented into a better condition of being wrought: The old Chaſe was foil'd, but not ſo abſolutely loſt, to the deſpair of a Retrieve; they had their Fathers Plat-form; moſt of the Materials would ſerve again, and who knew, but they might improve upon't? If they fail'd, 'twas but what others had done before 'em; and if it hit, there was a full amends for all: So readily do Drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men catch at Twigs, and (<hi>Epimetheus</hi> like) keep Hope in the bottom of the Box, when it had been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to have forborn the opening it.</p>
                  <p>Then as to the Carriers of it on: What were they but two or three Firſt-Rate-Diſcontents, who being out-witted in their point, gave themſelves up to that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151466:26"/>peaceable reſignation, of taking no notice of it, till they had contriv'd a Revenge? The Word was, The King hated them, or lov'd them not, which (to ſuch Men) was all one; nor could they believe, his Heir preſumptive (as they call'd him) ſhould be much fonder; and therefore, a Bill of Excluſion muſt ſecure all: And however the Houſe of Lords (to their Eternal Honour) threw it out, yet was it never ſet on foot again among the Commons? or that, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? Let it periſh as it lies, nor will I rub the Nap too hard, for fear of diſcovering the Thread.</p>
                  <p>And Laſtly for the end of it: The Title ('tis true) calls it an Act for preventing dangers, that may ariſe from <hi>Popiſh Recuſants.</hi> But what ſays every Man that wears not a Bibb, and who, if he belies not his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, cannot but confeſs, That the main drift, and end of it was to keep His now Majeſty from the Crown, by undermining Him in His Dependencies firſt, that they might the better afterward attack Him in His Perſon? It was againſt their Intereſt, that He ſhould come to be King, and therefore, 'twas but neceſſary, that they rid Him of His Friends, till (as the <hi>Gaderens</hi> by our Saviour) they cou'd get Him out of the Country. And can the King be ſafe, while ſuch a Law is in being? It may be much doubted: For when the Word of a King, that he will not alter Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as it is now eſtabliſh't by Law, is of no credit, without farther Security, what muſt the meaning of it be, but that they that are for having this Act ſtand, either dare not truſt Him, or could be well content,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151466:26"/>that it had taken effect? Or if it be only a point of Honour in the caſe, I would fain know, whither <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi>'s, nevertheleſs for his Oaths ſake, were any excuſe for cutting off the <hi>Baptiſt</hi>'s Head? I ſhould think not; inaſmuch as the keeping ſuch an Oath, did but add to the Crime, and he might have better askt God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs, for the making, than the breaking it. Where an Oath obliges not, leſs does Honour.</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>But may ſome ſay, ſhould not all Laws that concern Religion, be like thoſe of the</hi> Medes <hi>and</hi> Perſians, <hi>immutable?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Wee'll ſuppoſe it for once: But then what are become of all our own Statutes of that kind, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Edw.</hi> the <hi>6th?</hi> Or if we meaſure it by the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, what effect had that of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Daniel,</hi> but that it expos'd an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent to the Lions, and made <hi>Darius</hi> rather ſhuffle with his Authority, than diſoblige a Faction, which he might have cruſht with a Breath, as he did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards?</p>
                  <p>But to go on: Was there no danger from any other ſort of Recuſants? Was there no <hi>Oxford</hi> buſineſs? No <hi>Rye-Houſe?</hi> Was this, and the late King, to have been Murder'd in Maſquerade only? Yes, yes, (I hear 'em ſay) There was a Plot, and a Plot with a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! But 'twas a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot: Had not the King been kill'd in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Park, if <hi>Pickering</hi> had not ramm'd the Silver Bullet, into a Conſecrated skrew'd Gun, before the Powder, and at another time, the Flint been looſe? Did not <hi>Oates,</hi> and Parteners Swear it?
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151466:27"/>And did not the Rulers believe him, and the People, in him? And therefore, if neither Teſt, nor Excluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would do, was not <hi>Venient Romani</hi> ſufficient ground for an <hi>Aſſociation?</hi> Oh Hoe! <hi>Bene habet, nil plus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roge</hi>—Your Servant, Sir.—But was there no Republican Plot in the bottom? was not the truth of the one, ſlur'd on the World, under the diſguiſe of t' other? Such (I muſt confeſs) as ſuffer'd on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot, deny'd it to their laſt;— They were all (but one) <hi>Papiſts.</hi>—But, ſee the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity of the Godly! Not one of them, but confeſt theirs, with this tender diſtinction only, that they were guilty of the Conſpiracy, but not of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.—<hi>Habeat jam Roma pudorem!</hi> When would the others have done as much?</p>
                  <p>And after all this (to take in <hi>Hutton,</hi> and <hi>Crooke</hi>'s diſtinction) was not, <hi>Hannihal ad portas?</hi> Was there no <hi>Bellum flagrans?</hi> No actual War, at the time when His Majeſty granted thoſe Commiſſions? What was the then Rebellion in the <hi>Weſt?</hi> and that other, at the ſame time in <hi>Scotland?</hi> Clouds, no bigger than a Hand at firſt, but had they not like to have over-ſpread both Kingdoms? When <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>3d</hi> heard that <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi> was Landed with 7000 Men, he ſlighted it; but when it was told him they were but 300, he put Foot in Stirrup, as too truly preſaging, the Kingdom had invited him in. And what ſhould the King have done in this caſe, thrown Himſelf upon thoſe that would have Excluded Him, or truſt them of whom He had had former aſſurance?</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:151466:27"/>
                  <p>In ſhort, it remains that I ſpeak to His. Majeſtys yet continuing them in His Service: And truly (I conceive) the ſame Reaſon, and Law, will hold for both. For Inſurrections, and Rebellions,<note place="margin">Lord <hi>Bacon.</hi>
                     </note> being not written on Ice, that when the Body relenteth, the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion ſhould wear away, how can the King (who is Judge of the Expectant, as well as preſent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) deem Himſelf ſecure, while the Serpent, yet threatens with its Tail? God has ſignally proſper'd His Majeſtys Arms; but are His Enemies ſo much as willing, to be reclaim'd? They are beaten down that roſe up againſt Him, but is He ſure, they ſhall riſe no more? The Winds are laid ('tis true) but has the Sea yet left rouling? Or if it has, what means this <hi>Unda vulgi?</hi> Theſe new Murmurs, and Caballings of the People? Fire purgeth away Smoak and Aſhes, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apt Matter to enflame; and Living Bodies Purge, and Expel, what they cannot Convert, and Aſſimulate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Food and Nouriſhment. And ſhall Kings only take into their Boſom what they can neither convert, nor alter? The Argument were everlaſting, but I leave it; and from what I have ſaid before, thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Section, That His Majeſty, in the granting Commiſſions, to Perſons not qualify'd according to the ſaid Act, having done nothing, but what is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable by the Law of Reaſon, and the Laws of this Land, That the ſaid Commiſſions are well granted, notwithſtanding the ſaid Act. And the ſame alſo, for the yet retaining them in His Service.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:151466:28"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> That the Statute has created a Diſability in the Perſon, and other Objections, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</head>
                  <p>TO judge ones ſelf, is the way not to be judged; and to foreſee known Objections, is the way to prevent them from others; wherein never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, not to give them their proper Anſwers, were but to lend a Candle to another, and leave my ſelf in the dark.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. Object. 1. <hi>The Statute has created an incapacity in the Perſon, not qualify'd,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>by making him</hi> ipſo facto <hi>diſabled, to hold any Office,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the Office void.— As the 31ſt</hi> El. c. 6. <hi>That makes every corrupt Preſentation, Collation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and every Admiſſion, Inſtitution,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, void: And the perſon ſo corruptly taking, or procuring, a diſabled Perſon to have, or enjoy the ſame.—In like manner, the</hi> 5 Ed. 6. c. 16. <hi>That makes the buying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Offices void, and the Buyer, a diſabled Perſon to have, and occupy the ſame.—And the</hi> 3 El. c. 1. <hi>That every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Parliament, not taking the Oath of Supremacy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he enter the Houſe, ſhall be deemed, as if he had been never elected, and returned: Which alſo is a part of the Teſt, And how will the preſent Caſes differ, from the Diſability in the preſent Caſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:151466:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> For anſwer to which, I take a difference between <hi>Mala in Se,</hi> ſuch things as were meerly evil in themſelves at Common Law, before any Statute, and therefore indiſpenſible; and <hi>Mala prohibita,</hi> ſuch as were not ſimply evil in themſelves, but might have been lawfully done before they came to be prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſome Statute, and ſo, may be diſpenſt with:<note place="margin">11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. f. 11.</note> As in the preſent Caſe, That every Man not taking the Oaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the ſaid Act required, ſhall be diſabled, to hold any Office, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which implies, that he was capable before that Prohibition, for, all Exceptions prove the Rule. That the King may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Treaſon, Murder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is no Queſtion, but that He might diſpenſe with the practice of them, was never thought of, for ſuch a permiſſion, would be contrary to Original Juſtice, Moral Honeſty, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Equity, Humanity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not to be preſum'd in a private Man, much leſs in a Prince, as being a breach of that Truſt, God has repos'd in Him: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Mala prohibita,</hi> being otherwiſe indifferent in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and only evil in reſpect of the Prohibition, when that Reaſon ceaſeth, or becomes inconvenient, the Law alſo ſo far ceaſeth, as that the King, whoſe intereſt is the common good of the whole, may, nay ought to diſpenſe with it.</p>
                  <p>The ſix Articles in <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th</hi>'s time, on which, ſo many promiſcuouſly ſuffer'd,<note place="margin">31 <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 14</note> did the King do well or ill, in not diſpenſing with that Statute? If He did well, why is it laid as a charge on Him? and if He did ill, it muſt be acknowledg'd, that He had the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151466:29"/>power of doing otherwiſe, in diſpenſing with it: For a Man cannot be ſaid, to have done evill, but where it was in his power to have prevented that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and he did not. But to come to the particular Inſtances of <hi>Simony,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Simony,</hi> it is <hi>vox Eccleſiaſtica,</hi> and tho' it firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Malum prohibitum,</hi> by the Canon Law, whereof the Judges of the Common Law could take no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice before the Statute; yet, that it was <hi>Malum in Se,</hi> long before either Common, or Canon Law, appears by the judgment of St. <hi>Peter</hi> againſt <hi>Simon Magus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 8.20.</note> who thought the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt might be obtained by Mony: And tho' Preſentation, and the right of Patronage, be Temporal Matters, yet they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Spiritual, in reſpect of the thing, to which the Preſentment is made, which is Spiritual; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, every corrupt Preſentation, is a diſhonour to God, againſt the good of the Church, and an inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Common-Wealth; and withal, ſo much the more odious, in that it is always accompany'd with Perjury; for the <hi>Preſentee,</hi> at the time of his Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, takes an Oath, That he has made no <hi>Simoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acal</hi> Contract, Payment, or Promiſe, directly, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly, by himſelf, or any other, for the obtaining the ſame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore (nor without juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) has the Statute provided ſo ſeverely againſt it, in creating an indiſpenſible diſability in the perſon ſo offending.</p>
                  <p>Then for the buying of Offices: Not to put the Queſtion what it was before the Statute, or how pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151466:29"/>yet this I may venture to ſay, That (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, it is a bar to induſtry and Merit, and makes it as impoſſible for depreſt vertue to riſe, as to draw a Cable thro' the Eye of a Needle) it opens a way to the perverting of Juſtice, or at leaſt, begets an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in the Adminiſtration; for it is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, but that he that buys the Devil, will again try, how the Market goes with him.—<hi>Jure poteſt, emerat ille prius.</hi> And therefore, to keep the Eyes of the Wiſe open, and the Actions of the Juſt, from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perverted, it was as neceſſary in this matter, as the former, that the Statute ſhould create ſuch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible Diſability.</p>
                  <p>However admitting (not granting) it to be no evil in its ſelf, it receives this further Anſwer, That the <hi>Vendee,</hi> being diſabled by the Contract to take, the Office can never be legally veſted in him, after ſuch diſability accrewed, and conſequently, the King can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not remove it; which is not the preſent caſe, as I ſhall come to ſhew preſently.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, for what concerns the not taking the Oath of Supremacy; no Man (I preſume) will ſay, that it was an offence before the Statute; for though the not acknowledging the King to be Supream in His Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, was an offence at Common Law, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Statute, becauſe every Man being bound to the King, by reaſon of the Protection he receiv'd from Him, the Law of Nature oblig'd him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it, and return it in ſervice (whence the Kingdom was call'd,) <hi>The King's Ligeance</hi>—The
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151466:30"/>King,<note place="margin">27 <hi>E.</hi> 3 c. 1. 10.11. <hi>R</hi> 2. c. 1. 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 34, 35. c. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Liege-Lord.</hi> —And the People, His <hi>Liege-men</hi>) Yet the not teſtifying, and declaring it by the forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of an Oath, could not be ſaid to be an Offence, before there was ſome expreſs Law to exact ſuch an Oath; for, <hi>Ubi nulla Lex, ibi nullum peccatum.</hi> But now that the Statute has required an Oath, and that no Member, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not having firſt taken it, enter the Houſe, under the Penalty of being deem'd, as if he had been never elected, and return'd; as on the one hand (and if nothing intervene) it is become neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, to preſerve that Election, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So on the other, it is but a Penal Law, and conſequently, the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any ſuch Member ſhall come to ſit in the Houſe, may grant him Diſpenſation for not taking the ſaid Oath, and thereby prevent any diſability from ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crewing, which once accrewed, could not have been remov'd.</p>
                  <p>Now the difference between theſe Caſes, and that of an Officer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon this Statute, lies here.</p>
                  <p>The Firſt, was <hi>Malum in Se,</hi> and ſo indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
                  <p>The Second, Carries an impoſſibility; for the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice being void by the Contract, a Subſequent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, can have nothing to work upon.</p>
                  <p>But the Laſt, and that of an Officer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well agree; for if either of them, by his own neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, or refuſal, ſhall have incapacited himſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhall have obtained, the King's Diſpenſation, the diſability is fix't, beyond the poſſibility of remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it; but the Diſpenſation coming before the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151466:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>Diſability accrewed, it is prevented.</p>
                  <p>And how reaſonable it is that the King have this full power in Him will further appear, by bringing the Matter to a more familiar <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Says the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute you ſhall do every thing hereby required, or hold no Office.—Says the Perſon not ſo doing, I was born to obey, and ſerve the King; but the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances are hard upon me: The Statute is in the disjunctive; I'll take the eaſier part of it, and quit my employ.—But ſays the King, he is my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and I have uſe of his Service, which is due to me by the Law of Nature: Shall the King here, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer an inroad upon the Law of Nature, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible, or make uſe of His Royal Authority, in diſpenſing with this Statute, when without that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, that Service were loſt? I conceive He may: For the Statute its ſelf, ſhall have ſome reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able entendment to the Maker thereof. And ſhall any Man believe, it was the King's intention, when He paſt this Act, to exclude Himſelf from the power of judging, what were convenient, or inconvenient for the Government? And of what uſe were that judgment, if he ſaw an inconvenience, and could not ſtep over it? I do not ſay, the King may abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely diſcharge the ſaid Oaths; but if for Reaſons beſt known to Himſelf, He think fit to diſpenſe with them, what is that to us, who have no Authority to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it? Take away Knowledge to diſcern, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to weigh, and Reſolution to determine, and what will ye make of a Prince? His Majeſty foreſaw
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151466:31"/>a Storm coming, lay cloſe for it, and wrought it thro' with Reſolution: A Hand or two, might be enough at Helm, but it required many, to work the Ship: And whom in ſuch a caſe, would a Skipper chuſe? Such as had ſtuck to him in former Storms, or ſuch as had been for throwing him over-board, in a Calm? They might have been as handy perhaps, or better qualify'd, but the Ship was in danger, and what talk we of Formalities?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Object. <hi>But the King had other hands: A Loyal City, a truſty Militia,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> But is he bound to make uſe of them in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Caſes? Has not that City grown too faſt? May the King yet March thro' <hi>London</hi> without leave? Or take up Monys upon his Revenue, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Licenſe? I begin now, to be of opinion, he may, and withal hope, it ſhall long continue ſo. Then for the Militia: To give them their due, they were generally up, on the late <hi>Weſtern</hi> occaſion; but of no great uſe; what good did their numbers againſt <hi>William the Conquerour</hi>'s form'd Army? Or what's the reaſon the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> has ſo often follow'd the Fortune of a ſingle Battle? But that it has been fought, by an Uncommanded Multitude, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing, but their own Inclinations, believe God is departed from the beaten ſide, and conſequently deem it a ſin to tempt Providence with a Second. I will not ſay, but they may be made more ſerviceable; however, till that be, what hurt if the King make uſe of ſuch as are? In ſhort, as the Subject has his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151466:31"/>by the ſame Laws alſo, has the King his, <hi>i. e.</hi> His Prerogative: Nay, to imagine the contrary, were a Condradiction <hi>in Terminis:</hi> And what better were that Prerogative, if reſtrain'd, in the legal uſe, than a Long-wing'd Hawk, but ty'd to Fiſt? Shall a Man do nothing without conſulting his Wife? Or muſt the King call a Parliament upon every Emergency? I think not: For, <hi>Omnis Rex Angliae, eſt ſolus Rex,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Stam. pl. cor. 99.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; ſemper Rex,</hi> and there are many things he may do of himſelf, without Parliament.</p>
                  <p>The power of Peace, and War, is,<note place="margin">9 <hi>E.</hi> 4.4.</note> and was the King's, at Common Law; and our later Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, are but declaratory of that Ancient Law. —He may charge the Subject for defence of the Kingdom, without Parliament:<note place="margin">13 <hi>E.</hi> 4.14.</note> And the ſame did Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> in 1588.—Grant a Toll, upon the erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a new Fair—Market—Bridge—Ferry—Grant Pontage—Murage—Paveage,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rolls</hi> Abridg. 2d. part. <hi>171.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As there are many ancient Inſtances of it, in the <hi>3d. 7th.</hi> and <hi>32d.</hi> of <hi>Edw.</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> It may be ſaid ('tis true) the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject here, has a <hi>Quid, pro Quo;</hi> but what <hi>Quid pro Quo</hi> is it, That the King grants to one, or more Subjects, to have more priviledge, than others?—That he Erects Cities—Corporations—Gylds?—Founds Biſhopricks—Colleges—Hoſpitals? Grants Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to make By-Laws—Hold Courts—ſend Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes to Parliament? (no Poſitive Law, that I remember, ſtints the number to two: <hi>Wales,</hi> for the moſt part, ſend but one, and <hi>London</hi> four.) Is not all this by His Royal Charter? And what is it that ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151466:32"/>Him to that, but His Prerogative, which is the antienteſt part of the Law of the Land, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, the moſt Principal?</p>
                  <p>Nor is this all: The King by His Writ may Ordain alone.<note place="margin">9 <hi>E.</hi> 3.16.</note> A Writ of <hi>Ceſſavit</hi> was brought againſt the Tenants of <hi>Northumberland:</hi> They Petition the King, and ſhew, that they had been ſo harraſt, by Incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Scots,</hi> that they could not pay their Rents: The King by His Writ, Ordain'd a ſtay of Sute.—The King (before the convenience of Colleges) grants to the Scholars of <hi>Oxford,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">49 <hi>E.</hi> 3.18.</note> That they ſhould have the choice of Inns there: This is my Free-hold, ſays the Towns-Man, and the King cannot do it: But it is the King's Patent ſaid the Judges, and in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Learning, and therefore, a good Ordinance. Much more to which purpoſe, may be had in the Caſe of Ship-Mony, where (becauſe the Arguments are hard to be got by themſelves) they may be found in the Annals of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Object. <hi>But was not the Judgment for the King in that Caſe, afterwards vacated in Parliament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That it was ſo, <hi>de facto,</hi> is true: But that the Arguments of Sir <hi>Robert Holborn,</hi> and Mr. <hi>St. Johns</hi> (who argu'd it againſt the King) and of the Judges, <hi>Hutton,</hi> and <hi>Crooke</hi> (who had firſt under-written for the King, and afterwards gave their Opinions, againſt what they had ſo under-written) were by that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment held for Law, is alſo as true: And therefore if I have taken any of their Conceſſions, to prove my point for the King (as—<hi>Eas eſt &amp; ab hoſte doceri</hi>)
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151466:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>I know not, why it may not be the ſame Law now. And for the reſt of the Judges, (that gave their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions for the King, according to what they had firſt underwritten) they were accounted, Men Eminent in their time; and if the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Finch</hi> (a Gentleman, in whom Art, and Nature concurr'd, to make him Eloquent, and a long experience, dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; and who had been ſpeaker of the Parliament of <hi>3d. Car.</hi> 1. at what time the Petition of Right paſt) may be credited, Thoſe firſt Opinions, were ſo deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to His Majeſty, that no one Judge, knew the Opinion of the reſt, or the reaſon, that induc'd His Majeſty to demand it.</p>
                  <p>And now that I am upon this Matter, it is but a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice due to that King's Memory, that I open the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of it.</p>
                  <p>The Cards had long ſhuffling for ſome plauſible Trump, whereby to engage the People into a Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion: None more luckily turn'd up, wherein their Properties, ſeem'd to be concern'd, than this of Mr. <hi>Hambden,</hi> where the Caſe lay thus.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> in the <hi>9th. Car.</hi> 1. 1634. had ſet up the Northern Herring-fiſhing, on our Sea: <hi>Grotius</hi> had put out, three or four ſheets of Paper, which he calls, <hi>Mare Liberum:</hi> Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> learnedly encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd him, and as fully anſwer'd it, in his <hi>Mare Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum;</hi> by ſhewing, That before the <hi>Romans</hi> had ever to do in <hi>Britain;</hi> during their time; and ever ſince, the Dominion of the Narrow Seas was the Ancient, undoubted Right of the Crown of <hi>England:</hi> Pens
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151466:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>were too weak to decide the Matter: Mr. <hi>Noy,</hi> finds Precedents of Naval-aids, by ſole Authority of the King: Some few of the Commons except againſt it, as being out of Parliament, and againſt the Petition of Right: The firſt Writ is directed to the Major, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> to equip ſeven Ships of War, by a day cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ſufficiently provided (at their own Charges) of all things neceſſary, for 26 Weeks: From thence, Writs are ſent into the inland Counties: Moſt pay their proportion, which in the whole amounted to but 20000 <hi>per Menſ.</hi> thro' <hi>England:</hi> Mr. <hi>Hambden</hi> (of the County of <hi>Bucks,</hi> and whoſe ſhare, was but 20 <hi>s.</hi>) makes default: The King (<hi>an. Reg.</hi> 12.) Writes to the Judges, and demands their Opinion in Writing, Whither, when the good, or ſafety of the Kingdom in general is concern'd, the King may not by Writ under the Great Seal, command all His Subjects of this Kingdom, to furniſh a certain number of Ships, and Men, for ſuch time, as the King ſhall think fit, and by Law compel the doing it, in caſe of refuſal? And whither in ſuch a caſe, He is not the ſole Judge, both of the danger of the Kingdom, and when, and how, the ſame is to be prevented, and avoided? To this, every one of the 12 Judges did ſubſcribe in the Affirmative: Thereupon, proceſs is iſſu'd out of the Exchequer againſt <hi>Hambden:</hi> He demurs upon the Legality of the Writ: It is argu'd by all the Judges: The Majority of them, give their Opinions for the Writs; on which the Barons gave Judgment; which Judgment was in the <hi>16th.</hi> of the ſaid King,<note place="margin">27 <hi>Feb.</hi> 1640.</note> vacated in Parliament.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:151466:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>But (with due honour to all other Parliaments) what Parliament was it? It was begun in that Houſe of Commons, that afterward Murder'd that King: And tho' the <hi>Vacatur</hi> was <hi>per Conſiderationem, &amp; Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, Dominorum Spiritualium &amp; Temporalium in Curia Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamenti,</hi> &amp;c. Yet as to the Lords Spiritual, this may be ſaid, That a leading Man among them, then was, and from the time the Seal had been taken from him, had been alſo, a Diſcontent, nor was it hard to perſwade Perſons intereſted, that the Clergy were not liable to Secular Charges (whereas, aid in War—building of Bridges—and raiſing Forts, is that <hi>Trinoda neceſſitas,</hi> that binds the Clergy as well as the Laity.) And what got they by it, but that as it open'd a Gap, to ſeveral Acts, that paſt afterwards, ſo the King being leſſen'd in His Authority, was unable to defend them from a worſe <hi>Vacatur,</hi> which was put upon themſelves,<note place="margin">17 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. c. 22.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one full year after it? And for the Lords Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, (ſuch, or moſt of them, I mean, as follow'd not His Majeſty to <hi>Oxford</hi>) they joyn'd with thoſe Commons in making Ordinances, to raiſe Monies, and Arms, for the carrying on of that Rebellion which afterwards <hi>(inaudito Regibus exemplo)</hi> brought Him to the Block; and their Priviledge of Peerage, with Him. In ſhort, the matter is beyond excuſe; if they would not have had the Clock gone, they might have choſen, not to have wound it up, or taken off the Weights: For tho' that <hi>Vacatur</hi> of the Houſe of Lords upon the Judgment in the Exchequer, was confirm'd by an Act of Parliament, what was gotten by that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151466:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>20 <hi>s.</hi> which coſt the Kingdom more Treaſure, than it was at any one time worth, to have been ſold, and more Blood, than would have Conquer'd another?</p>
                  <p>Nor was it more than neceſſary, to have ſaid ſo much touching that Parliament, with whom the King was virtually, tho' not formally under a Force: For as preparatory to what enſu'd, they firſt got an Act of Parliament, that they ſhould not be Diſſolv'd, or Prorogu'd, but by Act of Parliament: And having gotten this Footing, in the ſame Runn, they procur'd others, for taking off, The ſeveral Courts of the Star-Chamber—Preſidencies of <hi>Wales,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See the Acts of the <hi>17. Car. 1.</hi>
                     </note> and the <hi>North</hi>—Dutchy of <hi>Lancaſter</hi>—Exchequer of the Palatinate of <hi>Cheſter</hi>—High-Commiſſion—And now to throw a Perſonal diſrepute upon His Majeſty, they bring in that Bill againſt Ship-mony, as having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſitated Him not to deny any thing—And having in the ſame heat, got the <hi>Stannaries,</hi> and the Statute 1 <hi>E.</hi> 2. <hi>de Militibus,</hi> taken off, and the Biſhops out of the Houſe of Lords, the very next Act that paſt, was the impreſſing Souldiers for <hi>Ireland</hi>—And what did they do with them?<note place="margin">See the King's Anſwer to their <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papers.</note> But (having driven the King from <hi>Whitehall,</hi> by Tumults) fought Him at <hi>Edge-Hill,</hi> with thoſe individual Forces. Thus, inch by inch, fell that goodly Oak of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Foreſt; His Roots, and Binders were cut off, and what wonder if His own weight brought Him down? Or that the People were ſo intent, on gathering the Sticks, that they wanted leiſure, to heed what was done?</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:151466:34"/>
                  <p>And now to cloſe this Section: If Authority with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Power, be but what <hi>Lucan</hi> ſays of <hi>Pompey—Magni nominis umbra</hi> (as without further proof, was verify'd in him,) That Government certainly, muſt be an imaginary nothing, or at beſt, but painted wings, that has not the power of preſerving its ſelf, as the Emergency, or Exigence of Affairs requires: Nor is it ever likely to be long liv'd, where it wants the Reſolution, to make it ſelf obey'd. It is ſaid of <hi>Saul,</hi> that <hi>he feared the people:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.24.</note> But it loſt him the Kingdom. And how probably can it be otherwiſe, when the People, ſhall be more at Liberty, than the Soveraign? Shall they ſtop at nothing for Subverting the Government, and is it reaſonable, the King be abridg'd, for the ſaving it? What hurt is it that <hi>Caeſar,</hi> have the things that are <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s, eſpecially, when the profit, and advantage is the Peoples? The contrary (I am ſure) has ever embroyl'd us, and he that goes no further, than our own Hiſtories, will find, That the more our Kings have been bound, the more have they ſhaken off thoſe Fetters; and the more it has been endeavour'd, to reſtrain their Rights, the more have they ever, exerted their Authority.</p>
                  <p>In a word, we have the Intereſt of a King for our Defence, and the Word of a King for our Security: and if an Act of Parliament cannot bar the King of any thing that is due to Him of Common right, how much better were it, to believe Him to be what we would have Him, and make him ſo; than by diſput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dividing <hi>Mathematical</hi> points, and engaging
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151466:35"/>our ſelves in impracticable Notions, catch at Shadows, and loſe the Subſtance? The Camel (in the Fable) might have kept his Ears, if he could have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented without Horns.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. VII.</hi> The Sum of the whole further aſſerted, and confirm'd, from ſeveral Statutes, and other Authorities of the Common-Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Have already prov'd the neceſſity of this Supream Power—That it is innate, and inherent in the Perſon of an abſolute Monarch.—What that is. —That the Kings of <hi>England</hi> are ſuch.—And ſpoken at large, to their power of Diſpenſing.—It remains now, that for a cloſe of the whole, I further ſhew,</p>
                  <p n="1">I. That there are divers things ſo incident in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the King, that it is not in the power of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to take them away.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. That both Kings and Parliaments have been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver tender of having them encroach't on, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the Savings, in ſeveral Statutes.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. That the Power of Diſpenſing, and granting <hi>Non Obſtantes</hi> to Penal Statutes, is one of thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, and that inſeparable.</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:151466:35"/>
                  <p n="4">IV. That Statutes derogatory to the Prerogative, have ſome of them been held for void, others recall'd, by the King alone.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. Examples of Perſonal Diſabilities, ſome, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Parliament: others, by Eccleſiaſtical Canons, diſpenſt with by the King; others, void of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. The King cannot deveſt Himſelf, or reſtrain His Succeſſor, of any regal Right, that is eſſentially in the Crown. Theſe are my Materials for covering the Houſe; I ſhall proceed to finiſh it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. And that there are many things ſo incident in power, to the King, that it is not in the power of a Parliament to take them away, Judge <hi>Hutton</hi> (of whom before) agrees it, with the reſt of the Judges, and Inſtances in the Caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>7th;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Annal</hi> Char. 1. f. 592.593.</note> and that a Parliament could not diſpoſe the Right of the Crown. —The Power of making Wars, and Leagues (which alſo was agreed by Judge <hi>Crooke</hi>)—The Power of Coin, and its value.—The ſole Power of Calling,<note place="margin">Ibid. <hi>582.</hi>
                     </note> Proroguing, and Diſſolving Parliaments.—And that no Law can be made without His conſent.—And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Monarchical Powers, and Prerogatives, which (ſaith he) to be taken away, were againſt Natural Reaſon; and further calls them, Incidents ſo inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that a Parliament cannot take them away.—For (in another place) they belong to His Crown, as Head, and Protector.—And again (both of them) An Act of Parliament, That the King ſhould have no aid of His Subjects, would not bind, becauſe it would
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151466:36"/>be againſt Natural Reaſon: Which was but a Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of what Judge <hi>Crawley,</hi> and others the Judges, had delivered in the ſame Caſe.—And further (ſays the ſaid Judge <hi>Crawley</hi>) you cannot have a King without Regal Rights, no not by Act of Parliament: And what are theſe Regal Rights, but the Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, which contains in its ſelf Matter of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription,<note place="margin">Plowd. <hi>332.</hi>
                     </note> and is conſequently, as inſeparable Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Both Kings, and Parliaments, have been ever tender, of having them encroacht on, as may appear by the Savings, in ſeveral Acts of Parliament. The <hi>St. Praerogativa Regis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3 <hi>E.</hi> 1.</note> cloſes thus, The King would not, that at any other time, His Conceſſions thereby made, ſhould turn in prejudice, to Him, or His Crown; but that ſuch Rights, as appertain to Him, ſhould be ſaved in all points.—So; the King will not draw any Aid,<note place="margin">25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. c. 5.</note> or Prize into Cuſtom, but by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Aſſent of all the Realm: Saving the antient Aids, and Prizes, due and accuſtomed—So; no Impoſition ſhall be ſet upon Wooll,<note place="margin">11 <hi>R.</hi> 2. c. 9.</note> Leather, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> other than as granted by Parliament; and if any be, to be nulled: Saving to the King His antient Right. —So;<note place="margin">1 <hi>H.</hi> 4. c. 6.</note> the King is content to be concluded, by the Wiſe Men of His Realm, touching the Eſtate of Him, and His Realm: Saving always His Liberty, <hi>i.e.</hi> His Prerogative. Now what's the meaning of thoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings? But that thoſe Parliaments conſidering, there might in after time, ſome new Accidents happen, which could not be then foreſeen, they bethought
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151466:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>themſelves of no better way of ſecuring againſt them, than by leaving 'em, to the King's Diſcretion: And therefore, when it is ſaid, The King will not do, but ſo, or ſo, what other can it be, but that the King will not ordinarily do otherwiſe? And that it was not the Parliaments intent, but that in Caſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, He ſhould make uſe of His antient Right. And what antienter Right, than the Service of the Subject, for defence of the Kingdom? Nor is it to be thought, but when the Law aſſigns the King the defence of the Kingdom, it preſumes Him alſo, the power, to raiſe the means for the doing it: Or elſe, it were but the charge of a defence, without the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and means: And if the King could not do this out of Parliament, then were the Parliament the ſole Judge, and not the King, which alſo were contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory to the free Majeſtick Power of a Monarch.</p>
                  <p>And if this be not enough, there is yet another Statute, that makes it clear: For when it ſays, no Man ſhall be compell'd out of his Shire,<note place="margin">1 <hi>E.</hi> 3. c. 5.</note> but when neceſſity requires, and then, ſhall be done as in times paſt: How is that? If the King before that Statute could not have don't, that (But) had been to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and if the King before that, could have don it (as I have ſhewn what was the conſtant practice, of His Father's, and Grand-father's times) it is a plain Confeſſion of that Right, and a modeſt entreaty, that He will not ordinarily make uſe of that diſcretionary power, but as Neceſſity requires.</p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:151466:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Other while again we have it by Implication, where ſuch Savings have been omitted. As when the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Right was in agitation,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Car.</hi> 1.</note> the Commons, to take off all doubt of encroaching on the King's Rights, made this Proteſtation, That it was not their intention thereby, to bind the King, from His ancient Right; which the King alſo, on His paſſing that Bill, takes particular notice of; however it comes to be left out in the laſt Edition of the Statutes at large; as that Clauſe, ſaving the King's Regality, in the Statute 2 <hi>R.</hi> 2. St. 2. c. 4. for Confirmation of Liberties, is omitted in all of them. Nor was this Proteſtation made without Reaſon; for it had been long before declar'd,<note place="margin">42 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 4 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 357.</note> that they could not conſent to any thing in Parliament, that tended to the diſinheriſon, of the King, or His Crown, to which they were Sworn.— It was,<note place="margin">18 <hi>E.</hi> 3. c. 4.</note> and is, a part of the Judges Oath.—And of the Coronation Oath, That He ſhall keep all the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Dignities of the Crown,<note place="margin">Cowel. Tit. Oath.</note> in all manner whole, without miniſhment; and the Rights of the Crown hurt, decayed, or loſt, to His Power, ſhall call again into the antient Eſtate: From which it is undeniable, but that the King has antient Rights; and being ſo, it neceſſarily follows, That they cannot be taken away, till prov'd to be forfeited: And if for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited, who ſhall ſit in Judgment on it, when the King having no Peer in His Realm,<note place="margin">3 <hi>E.</hi> 3.19.</note> cannot be judged Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; nor by His own Authority; and other, there is none in His Realm.</p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:151466:37"/>
                  <p n="3">3. The Power of Diſpenſing, or granting <hi>Non Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes</hi> to Penal Statutes, is one of thoſe antient Rights. Sir <hi>Robert Holburn</hi> (of whom alſo before) confeſſes it. The King (ſaith he) may diſpenſe with Penal Laws, and make them as none:<note place="margin">Ibid Ann. <hi>552.</hi>
                     </note> For there is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity that this Power ſhould be in ſome Body: No Law ſays the King, ſhall not do it; and Acts of Parliament, are but <hi>Leges temporis.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Book of Law. <hi>82.</hi>
                     </note> —The King (ſaith Sir <hi>Henry Finch</hi>) hath an abſolute power over all; for by a <hi>Non Obſtante,</hi> he may diſpenſe with a Statute Law, tho' the Statute ſay, ſuch Diſpenſation ſhall be meerly void.—And Judge <hi>Barkely,</hi> to the ſame purpoſe: A Penal Law is made, and a Clauſe in it,<note place="margin">Ibid. Ann. <hi>57<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </note> that the King ſhall not diſpenſe with it: A <hi>Non Obſtante</hi> may be made to that <hi>Non Obſtante,</hi> for it taketh away a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Power out of the Kings Hands—whoſe Perſon,<note place="margin">Ibid. Ann. <hi>59<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </note> and Royal Prerogative cannot be reſtrain'd (ſaith <hi>Judge Jones</hi>) no, not by Act of Parliament.—And if there yet remain'd a doubt, Sir <hi>Edw. Coke</hi> will paſs for Authority (when ſpeaking of ſome Statutes, that had reſtrain'd the King's Power of granting Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons) his words are theſe;<note place="margin">3 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 236.</note> But it hath been conceived (which we will not queſtion) That the King may Diſpenſe with theſe Laws by a <hi>Non Obſtante,</hi> be it ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, or ſpecial. Now in as much as this power is not in the People, or deriv'd from them, it follows (as before) that it be Original, Innate, and inherent in the Perſon of the King, <hi>Inter jura ſummae Majeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> and conſequently, inſeparable.</p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:151466:38"/>
                  <p n="4">4. Statutes derogatory to the Prerogative, have, ſome of them been held for void; others, recall'd. An Act of Parliament (ſaith Sir <hi>J. Banks</hi>) extends not to take away any,<note place="margin">Ibid. Ann. <hi>569.</hi>
                     </note> thing that belongs to the Crown of Common Right; for it is <hi>(Lexterrae)</hi> the Law of the Land. The Liberties of the Subject, are by proceſs of time, become of Common Right, an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt which,<note place="margin">8 <hi>Coke</hi> 118.</note> were void: And can the Kings Prerogative, from which thoſe Liberties were at firſt deriv'd, be of leſs right? Of leſs force in Law? When it is ſaid,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 3. <hi>N.</hi> 13.</note> An Act of Parliament contrary to the Fundamental Laws, and Prerogative of the King, ſhall loſe the Name of a Statute.—It binds not the King (ſaith Judge <hi>Vernon</hi>) and if it doth not bind,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>id. Ann. <hi>581.</hi>
                     </note> what is it but void? And his Reaſon is, becauſe it is Derogatory to the Prerogative.—For (as Judge <hi>Jones</hi>) The Power of the King is a Special Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>id. Ann. <hi>592.</hi>
                     </note> and if good at Common Law, takes away the Statute,<note place="margin">Ibid. Ann. <hi>598.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>pro bono publico.</hi>—And (the Lord Chief Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron <hi>Davenport</hi>) it would be <hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> and ſo void, becauſe it would deſtroy the <hi>Jus Regale.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that the King may revoke ſuch a Derogatory Statute,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> prerog. <hi>180.</hi>
                     </note> we have the Authority of Serjeant <hi>Rolle.</hi> And that it is no new thing, there are ſeveral Inſtances.—King <hi>John</hi> by Charter (which, ſays <hi>Gaſcoign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> is no Statute,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>E.</hi> 4.19</note> nor was it ever taken for ſuch, but where it concurs with <hi>Magna Charta</hi>) grants, That (<hi>Nullum Scutagium, vel Auxilium,</hi> &amp;c.) No Tenant by Knights Service, ſhall be compelled to make a Voyage, to War againſt the <hi>French,</hi> or <hi>Scots;</hi> or aid be taken,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151466:38"/>without common conſent; but to make his Eldeſt Son a Knight: Marry his Eldeſt Daughter: And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem his Perſon. But when was this granted? Was it not at <hi>Running-Mead,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">An. Reg. <hi>17.</hi>
                     </note> at what time there were Banners diſplay'd, and the Barons and Commonalty in open Rebellion againſt him? An odd <hi>Modus te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendi Parliamentum.</hi> And ſhall it be ſaid, an enforc't Act, from a diſtreſt King, ſhall bind the Crown? Or, ſhall the Subject only plead <hi>Duritiam, &amp; Minas?</hi> It is ſomewhat yet, that it has had no Confirmation, in ſo many Parliaments ſince; and what difference (in ſubſtance) whither the Candle be put out, or go out of its ſelf, but that it leaves a Stench behind it?—However, the next is in point.</p>
                  <p>Some things derogatory to the Crown had been enacted, in <hi>Edw.</hi> the <hi>3d</hi>'s time: As,<note place="margin">15 <hi>E.</hi> 3.</note> As, that no Peer ſhould be queſtion'd, but in Parliament.—No Great Officer remov'd, but in Parliament.—No Clergy-Man, come before Temporal Judges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The King the ſame year, on better advice, revokes, and Nulls them: as contrary to the Laws of the Realm; drawn from Him againſt His Will; and prejudicial, to the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of His Crown.<note place="margin">4 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 52</note> But (ſays Sir <hi>Edw. Coke</hi>) the Printed Book ſuppoſes, there was another Parliament, in the ſaid 15. <hi>E.</hi> 3. Whereas in Truth, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that repeal'd them, was in <hi>Quind. Paſ.</hi> 17. <hi>E.</hi> 3. In anſwer to which, it ſhall be enough to me, that he owns, theſe Acts were made, the ſaid 15. <hi>E.</hi> 3. as in Fact they were, and that the Parliament of that year, made no Repeal of them, which alſo is as true; and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151466:39"/>I hold with him: But with this; That it was a ſingle Act of the King's, and out of Parliament; for the King, the ſame <hi>15th.</hi> year conſidering, how in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, He had diſrob'd Himſelf of His Authority, by His Writ, or Royal Mandate, to the reſpective She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs (which carries not the Stile of an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or any the other the Acts of His time) Wills, and Commands them, that for the Reaſons aforeſaid, they proclaim thoſe Acts, Null: As may be ſeen in the Printed Statutes (in a particular Writ, to the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff of <hi>Lincoln</hi>) and a wonder it is, this alſo, had not been left out among the reſt. But now to come up with him: The Contrivers of theſe Acts (for it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by them, that the Grandees only, not the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, were concern'd in them) ſaw the King had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted His Prerogative, and wanted not Reſolution of going thro' with it; and knowing, themſelves were to be the ſame Perſons in the next Parliament, thought it high-time, to comply with the preſent; and ſince the King would not come down to them, to come up to Him, and by making it their own Act, ſtifle ſuch a ſignal precedent for the Prerogative: And therefore, in the <hi>17th.</hi> of the ſaid King (which Sir <hi>Edw. Coke</hi> mentions) thoſe Acts were repealed in Parliament, and further declared, That they ſhould loſe the Name of Statutes, as being contrary to the Laws, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative. Which (with all due Submiſſion) I leave to every Man's Examination; yet withal think, that he that reported <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Caſe, might have forborn this, or done it more Candidly.—But the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151466:39"/>of the <hi>15th.</hi> of His Father, took better Meaſures; there had been Ordinances in the <hi>5th. Edw. 2d.</hi> That the King could not make War, without the aſſent of His Barons: The Parliament ſaw the King reſolv'd to have them off, and they generouſly prevented Him, by a Repeal of their own, as prejudicial,<note place="margin">Rot. Parl. <hi>15.</hi> E. <hi>2.</hi> M. <hi>31.</hi>
                     </note> to the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Power of a King.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Examples of Perſonal Diſabilities, ſome crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Parliament: Others, by Eccleſiaſtical Canons, diſpenſt with by the King: Others, void in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Wherein alſo, I do but further confirm, what I have before laid down, and from the practice of paſt times, make a reaſonable Interpretation of the preſent. The St. 4 <hi>H.</hi> 4. c. 31. ſays no <hi>Welſh-man</hi> ſhall be Juſtice, or other Officer, in any part of <hi>Wales:</hi> Yet the King may diſpenſe with it.—So the 8 <hi>R.</hi> 2. c. 2. ſays, no Man of Law ſhall be Juſtice of Aſſize,<note place="margin">12 Coke 18.</note> or Gaol-Delivery in his own Country, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the County where he was Born, or doth Inhabit (for ſo the 33. <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 24. explains it.) under the Penalty of an 100 <hi>l.</hi> And yet the King's diſpenſing with it, has been, and is every days practice.—And if it were not for the King's Licenſe, for Importing, and Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſeveral Commodities, prohibited by Statute, Informers, and their Auxiliaries, (Knights of the Poſt) might live well enough, without the Sweat of their Conſciences But admitting theſe may not come up (as I ſee not where they fall ſhort) The 13. <hi>H.</hi> 6. c. 8. is in point. No Sheriff (ſays that Statute) ſhall continue in his Office above one year, under the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151466:40"/>of 200 <hi>l.</hi> and every Patent to that purpoſe, to be void, notwithſtanding the Clauſe of <hi>Non Obſtante:</hi> And the perſon, for ever after diſabled, to bear the Office of Sheriff. And yet <hi>Edw.</hi> the <hi>4th,</hi> made a Sheriff for life, <hi>cum clauſula Non Obſtante</hi> to that Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, and adjudged good,<note place="margin">2 <hi>H.</hi> 7.6.</note> by all the Juſtices.—Nor ſeems the Caſe of the Lord <hi>De la Ware,</hi> to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together wide of the matter. <hi>William Weſt,</hi> Nephew, and Heir, of <hi>Tho.</hi> Lord <hi>De la Ware,</hi> had been diſabled by Act of Parliament,<note place="margin">3 <hi>E.</hi> 6.</note> to claim any Lands, Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from his ſaid Unkle, for his natural Life only:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>8</hi> Eliz.</note> 
                     <hi>Thomas</hi> dies: The Queen reſtores <hi>William:</hi> And by new Creation, to the ſame Title, calls him to Parliament, where he had place as puny Baron, and dies:<note place="margin">11 <hi>Coke</hi> 1.</note> Now the Caſe, as it is reported by Sir <hi>Ed. Coke,</hi> relates only to this, whither the new Lord <hi>De la Ware,</hi> ſhould take his place to the antient Barony, by Writ, or according to his Father's Creation, by Patent? and reſolv'd, he ſhould have it according to the antient Barony, which at the time of the new Creation, was only Suſpended. But I make this other uſe of it, That an Act of Parliament in one King's Reign, barr'd not the Succeſſor, of the Service of that Subject, becauſe it was due, by a Title paramount the diſability, <hi>viz.</hi> The Law of Nature: Here was a manifeſt diſability, created by Parliament, in the Perſon of <hi>William,</hi> and the intent of the Act was, he ſhould not ſerve in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as Lord <hi>De la Ware:</hi> The Queen finds ſhe had uſe of his Service, as Lord <hi>De la Ware,</hi> and by new Creation, enables him to perform it: So then,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151466:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>whither he ſate in Parliament by vertue of the old Dignity, or new Creation, it matters not: He ſate in Parliament: The diſability was remov'd, and the Queen had his Service.</p>
                  <p>And beſides this, there are other Matters, contrary to the uſage of the Realm, and Eccleſiaſtical Canons, in force among our ſelves, that have been diſpenſt with by our Kings, and that, out of Parliament. The Clergy, by that uſage, and their own Canons, are diſabled to bear Secular Offices,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 121.</note> and the doing other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, has been complain'd of in Parliament (45 <hi>E.</hi> 3.) yet our Kings have frequently diſpenſt with them in it, and made them Chancellors, Treaſurers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> both before, and ſince the Reformation; and he ſcandals the Authority of both, that will allow nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.—On the other hand, <hi>Cromwell</hi> in <hi>Henry 8th</hi>'s time, was <hi>Merè Laicus,</hi> yet the King made him His Vicegerent in <hi>Eccleſiaſticis,</hi> however otherwiſe inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitated, by the ſame uſage, and Canons.</p>
                  <p>And that there have been ſeveral Perſonal Diſabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, created by Parliament, yet void in themſelves, we have the ſeveral Examples of <hi>Edw.</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> (who in the Blood of His Father <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi>) was diſabled from claiming the Crown.—<hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>6th,</hi> to reaſſume it.—<hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi> attainted by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.—Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively Excluded by the ſame Authority.—And yet, the acceſſion of the Crown, clear'd thoſe Diſabilities, without a Repeal; and what better could there have been dream't, from the late Bill of Excluſion?</p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:151466:41"/>
                  <p n="6">6. Laſtly, (and to cloſe all) The King cannot deveſt Himſelf, or reſtrain His Succeſſor, of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Right, that is eſſentially in the Crown, <hi>i.e.</hi> really annext to His Perſon, as King: Becauſe it would be in prejudice of the Crown, in making Him leſs King, than He ought to be. Nor are any of the King's Grants, or Conceſſions, to be underſtood otherwiſe, than <hi>Salvo Jure Coronae:</hi> For by the ſame Reaſon, that any one part may be ſeparated, may alſo more; and ſo from one thing to another, even all at laſt, and very well if it holds a Dukedom of <hi>Venice.</hi> Whereas, <hi>Quae Juriſdictionis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bract.</hi> l. 2. c. 24.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; Pacis ſunt, ad nullum pertinent, niſi ad Coronam, &amp; dignitatem Regiam, nec à Coronâ Seperari poſſunt, cùm faciant ipſam Coronam.</hi> Such things (ſaith he) as concern the Supream Authority, and Peace of the Kingdom, belong to none, but the Crown, and Royal Dignity, nor can they be ſeparated from the Crown, in as much as they are the very things that make it a Crown. This <hi>Bracton,</hi> was a Judge in <hi>Hen.</hi> the <hi>2d</hi>'s time, during the heat of the Barons Wars; and what he means by thoſe Words, but that the Crown were nothing without that Supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and the power of executing it, were worth his explaining, that would draw any other ſenſe from them: And if he ſhall not, it is but reaſonable that he confeſs, That the Crown is, and ought to be preſerv'd entire; and as it will not admit of any falſe Metal to embaſe it, will leſs endure any Clogs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumber it. I ſpeak not of Popular, or Conſular States, or what may have been practis'd in them:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151466:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>Or Elective Kingdoms, where tho One may bear the Title, and Honour of a Prince, He has not <hi>Merum Imperium,</hi> the Supream Power of an Abſolute Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, but is Himſelf ſubject to that Power, which is tranſcendent to His, and appertaineth to the State. But of the King of <hi>England,</hi> over whom the States have no power, in as much as all Power, and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is deriv'd from Him—<hi>de Lumine Lumen;</hi> but (as before) <hi>Salvo Jure Coronae:</hi> For the Royal Dignity is indiviſible, and every Subject owes Him <hi>Liege Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, De vita, membro &amp; terreno honore,</hi> for Life, Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and Earthly Honour; nor can any Earthly Power diſcharge him of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>William the Conqueror</hi> created <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> (his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew) Hereditary Earl of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and gave him the County in Fee, <hi>Ita Liberè ad gladium,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">4 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 211.</note> 
                     <hi>ut ipſe Rex tenebat Angliam, ad Coronam:</hi> To hold it as free by his Sword, as Himſelf-held <hi>England,</hi> by his Crown; Yet this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted him not from remaining a Subject.—So, a Grant to the Abbot of St. <hi>Bartholomew,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">14 <hi>H.</hi> 7.11.</note> to be as free in his Lands, as the King in His Crown: Yet he was ſtill a Subject, and ſhall pay a fine.—But theſe (may be ſaid) were the ſingle Acts of a King, and out of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: We'll ſee now, what a Parliament could do. <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> by His Letters Patents cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>Robert de Vere</hi> (Earl of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> and Marqueſs of <hi>Dublin</hi>) to be Duke of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and grants to him for life, <hi>Totam terram, &amp; Dominium Hiberniae—Portus Maris,</hi> &amp;c. The whole Land and Dominion of <hi>Ireland</hi>—The Sea Ports—The Patronage of all Biſhopricks—To ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151466:42"/>a Chancellor, Treaſurer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galities within that Kingdom, as fully, as Himſelf, or any of His Progenitors, ever had them: And theſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents,<note place="margin">9 <hi>R.</hi> 2.</note> were authoriz'd by Parliament, <hi>Aſſenſu Praelatorum, Ducum, Procerum, &amp; Communitatis Angliae in Parliamento:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">4 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 357.</note> But what became of it? They were Inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Regalities, and it fell to nothing.—So 4 years after, the King by the ſame Authority, gave the Title of Duke of <hi>Acquitaine,</hi> to His Unkle <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt;</hi> and that alſo, came to nothing: For that was one of the Titles, and Stiles of the Crown, and could not be granted. All which may be reſolv'd into this, That a Kingdom without full Regalities, is but the burthen of a Night-Mare; Men think they have ſomething, when in Truth it is nothing, but an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weildy weight.</p>
                  <p>And as the Crown it ſelf is entire, ſo alſo ought the Deſcent to be as entire. The ſame <hi>Rich.</hi> the <hi>2d,</hi> devis'd certain Treaſure to His Succeſſors, upon condition to obſerve all the Acts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at a Parliament held the 21. of His Reign:<note place="margin">4 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 42.</note> and it was held unjuſt, and unlawful, becauſe it reſtrain'd the Liberty of the Kings His Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors. —And on the ſame ground is it, that the King cannot grant a judicial Office,<note place="margin">1 <hi>R.</hi> 3.4.</note> ſo as it ſhall not be void, againſt His Succeſſor.—Nor priviledge of Sanctuary for Treaſon,<note place="margin">1 <hi>H.</hi> 7.26.</note> to bind His Succeſſor.—And the <hi>Ceſſavit</hi> before mentioned, was good during the King's Life, but not againſt His Succeſſor: Nor was it ſo much the Death of the King that vacated them, as that the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of granting them, being an inſeparable Incident of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151466:42"/>the Crown, that alſo deſcended to the Succeſſor, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Crown.</p>
                  <p>To bring this home, King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> made this Act: He had the Entierty of the Crown in Him, and might have as well diſpenſt with it, as Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> did with Hers, of the <hi>1ſt.</hi> of Her Reign, for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue. And if the ſame Crown, be now deſcended to His Majeſty, why may not He rather diſpenſe with this Statute, as being an Act of His Brother's, not His own? Or if otherwiſe, how is it the Crown of <hi>England?</hi> Suppoſe King <hi>Charles 2d.</hi> had given up His Crown (as once in His Reign, there wanted very little of the asking it) would it have bound this King? I conceive not.<note place="margin">Daniel<hi>'s Hiſt. of</hi> Engl. f. 120. <hi>Ibid.</hi> 138.</note> 
                     <hi>Rich. 1ſt.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd it to the Emperor.—King <hi>John</hi> (what in him lay) ſubjected it.—<hi>Hen.</hi> the <hi>3d</hi> granted to <hi>Monfort,</hi> and his Complices, all His Regal Power,<note place="margin">Ibid. <hi>177.</hi>
                     </note> and abſolv'd His Subjects of their Obedience <hi>(ac ſi in nullo nobis teneren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur)</hi> if He infring'd the Charter, then made them.— <hi>Rich. 2d.</hi> gave it up.—And <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. did what He could, to have turn'd it out of the right Channel.—But what became of all? The firſt, and the third, broke thro' it in their own time, and the right Heirs of the others, found it no bar to them, and all the Regalities of the Crown, came back with it, as being impoſſible, it could ſubſiſt without them.</p>
                  <p>In ſhort, the ſame weight, requires the ſame Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: Nor will it be ſaid of Monarchy, as of the Sea, what it loſes in one place, it gains in another: No, That only can wreſtle a Fall with Time, that keeps it ſelf
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151466:43"/>entire, in all its parts: For the firſt diminution, is but a ſtep to diſſolution; as may be ſeen in Buildings, take off any conſiderable Pillar, and the Fabric leans: There may ('tis true) be a kind of Majeſty, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in mighty Ruines; but Men rarely come near them, for fear of being involv'd in them. In a word, we have a memorable inſtance of this in our late Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd Sovereign, King <hi>Char.</hi> I. He had made more Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, than might have been thought poſſible to have been askt (but that nothing was impoſſible for the Men of that time to attempt) but when they came to touch that Quick of His Regalities, He choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to truſt Providence with His Kingdoms, than ſave His Life, and them, with the acceptance of an embas'd Crown, or ſtain His Memory, with a Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſo inglorious. Nor can I quit the Argument with a greater authority.</p>
                  <p>And therefore to conclude this firſt part, and for the Reaſons aforeſaid, I conceive, His Majeſty may well diſpenſe with Penal Statutes; and more particularly, with this Statute.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:151466:43"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>WHat has been the common wont to the Reader, ſutes better with this Matter, to give it here; and that is, The occaſion of what I have Written, which lies thus.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty through the greateſt of Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and the repeated, but fruitleſs At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of an Excluſion, had by the Death of His late Royal Brother King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, come at laſt, to the Crown; nor was it ſcarce on His Head, when a double Rebellion, did more than threaten it: Upon this, The King (ſole Judge of the danger of the Kingdom, and in what manner to avoid it) being little other than neceſſitated, either to truſt thoſe few He had try'd, or thoſe many others, that had been for Excluding Him, grants Commiſſions to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:151466:44"/>Perſons, not qualify'd according to the ſaid Statute <hi>25th. Car. 2d.</hi> With a <hi>Non Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante</hi> to that Statute: This begat ſome Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Diſputes, touching the King's Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Power; and thoſe, a Deſire in me, of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying my own Judgment; and being confirm'd my ſelf, I thought it my Duty to ſtrengthen others.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, It was Written about <hi>Eaſter, 1686,</hi> and has but lately come to my Hands again; by which means, I wanted the advantage of rivetting it, with that Solemn Judgment in point (in <hi>B. R.</hi>) in the Caſe of <hi>Godwin, verſ.</hi> Sir <hi>Edw. Hales,</hi> upon this Statute, which was not till the <hi>Trinity</hi> Term following: However, finding That, ſo great a Foundation, for a further Superſtructure, I went on with the Argument, upon that other Teſt. Act, <hi>30. Car. 2d.</hi> as it ſeverally reſpects a Peer of the Realm, and a Member of the Houſe of Commons; and finiſht it with this, That the King might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſpenſe with that Statute alſo: But this being out of my Hands, and having little to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151466:44"/>it by, but ſome imperfect Notes, I thought fit to Publiſh this Firſt Part for the preſent, with aſſurance nevertheleſs, of that Second Part to follow it: though neither of them had been further thought on, but that the ſame Duſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rais'd anew, it was but Charity, to keep it from blinding the People.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
